<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>test on Robin Lovelace&#39;s website. Energy. Transport. Technology. Change the World.</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in test on Robin Lovelace&#39;s website. Energy. Transport. Technology. Change the World.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Six great things about UseR! 2019</title>
      <link>/2019/07/13/user2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/13/user2019/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/jquery/jquery.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leafletfix/leafletfix.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4-compressed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/rstudio_leaflet/rstudio_leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-binding/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-providers/leaflet-providers.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-providers-plugin/leaflet-providers-plugin.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/HomeButton/home-button.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/HomeButton/home-button.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/HomeButton/easy-button-src.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/PopupTable/popup.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/datatables-css/datatables-crosstalk.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/datatables-binding/datatables.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/dt-core/css/jquery.dataTables.min.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/dt-core/css/jquery.dataTables.extra.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/dt-core/js/jquery.dataTables.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/crosstalk/css/crosstalk.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/crosstalk/js/crosstalk.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;UseR! is the highest profile and, I believe, most popular annual meeting for R enthusiasts, known affectionately as ‘UseRs’ for the purposes of the event. For those who have been living under a stone for the past decade ;) R is an open source statistical programming language that has seen explosive growth since ‘data science’ became a buzzword. Although I’ve been using R for around a decade, and heavily for around five years, &lt;a href=&#34;http://user2019.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;UseR! 2019&lt;/a&gt; was the first UseR! I attended. I went with some preconceptions: I thought it would be like previous R events that I had attended, including the European R Users Meeting (ERUM) and SatRdays, but bigger. That was true, but it was bigger and better, exceeding my expectations in many ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://user2019.r-project.org/static/img/useR2019.png&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite only seeing part of it (I missed the tutorials on the Tuesday and the latter part of the final day on Friday), I learned many things from it. Inspired by the ‘useR aftRglow’, I wrote some of these down on the train journey back home. The result is this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://user2019.r-project.org/organization/&#34;&gt;organising committee of User! 2019&lt;/a&gt; (hats off to you for an amazing event) has lessons for anyone thinking of putting on a successful event for research, software development, or anything aiming to encourage a friendly symposium vibe. Here are the top six things that made User! 2019 great from my perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;diverse-formats&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1. Diverse formats&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes going to events, and especially academic conferences (mentioning no names &lt;code&gt;*cough*&lt;/code&gt; take note organisers of &lt;a href=&#34;https://annualmeeting.aag.org/&#34;&gt;AAAG&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rgs.org/research/annual-international-conference/&#34;&gt;RGS-IBG&lt;/a&gt; and other events with many presentation sessions), can feel undergoing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-35038429&#34;&gt;death by PowerPoint&lt;/a&gt;. A very slow, boring death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UseR! was different. Aside from the fact that many of presenters wouldn’t &lt;em&gt;be seen dead&lt;/em&gt; in front of PowerPoint slides, preferring instead more reproducible and flexible formats enabled by packages such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://slides.yihui.name/xaringan/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xaringan&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ioslides&lt;/code&gt;, the diversity of formats and quality of the talks kept me on my toes in every session I attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organisers had clearly given some thought to tackle this issue. Instead of having only a couple of talk types (e.g. 15 minute presentation, 1 hour keynote) a range of formats were supported, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Morning/afternoon tutorials, which took place on the Tuesday, allowing people to learn in depth about new methods/packages/approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A ‘tidyverse development’ day, which apparently involved physically taking issues and working on them in parallel, with a gong struck for every Pull Request accepted (this makes me wonder if the same technique can be used in other software ecosystems).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poster sessions, perhaps not an innovative thing in its own right, but at UseR! the poster showing session was preceded by Lightning Talks of ~1 minute each, so participants could identify which posters they would most like to visit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lightning talk sessions, where participants had 5 minutes to convey the core message of their research. These sessions were organised in themes and I chaired ‘Applications and Methods’ session, which contained some fascinating work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were still plenty of standard presentation sessions, but even in those sessions, the diversity kept things engaging. Colin Gillespie went into stand-up comedy mode to deliver a vital message: that simple changes can improve the security of computer systems using R. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mine_%C3%87etinkaya-Rundel&#34;&gt;Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel&lt;/a&gt; used the metaphor of cooking to highlight the importance of digital learning environments for effective classrooms: would you rather cook in a unfinished kitchen or a complete one? Use of a stable, in browser interface, as shown in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minebocek/status/1148904275550121984&#34;&gt;Data Science in a Box&lt;/a&gt; project, can overcome the barrier of software installation to research, with clear implications for organisations: get a working instance of RStudio Server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the Keynotes were diverse, as can be seen from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://user2019.r-project.org/program/&#34;&gt;UseR website&lt;/a&gt;. There wasn’t just one central ‘keynote speaker’ at the event but 6, half of whom were women, and with representatives from commercial, academic and &lt;a href=&#34;http://user2019.r-project.org/program/#julien&#34;&gt;non-profit&lt;/a&gt; organsiations. The diversity of topics they covered was also impressive. They ranged from Bettina Grün’s highly technical yet accessible keynote on new models and packages for clustering data to Joe Cheng’s talk on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/shinymeta&#34;&gt;shinymeta&lt;/a&gt;. It was roller coaster ride to the publication of this just open-sourced package, which enables shiny apps to generate scripts underlying the dynamic results. This could enable step change in the level of reproducibility of interactive web applications (vested interest: I’m the lead developer of the large shiny application, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pct.bike/&#34;&gt;Propensity to Cycle Tool&lt;/a&gt; that would benefit from being more reproducible).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the keynote speeches are available on YouTube, as disseminated in the Tweet below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;All the keynote lectures were available live on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RConsortium?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@RConsortium&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/YouTube?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#YouTube&lt;/a&gt; channel here:&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/otDzmY2UND&#34;&gt;https://t.co/otDzmY2UND&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Very soon, you&amp;#39;ll find the edited version (with video). keep posted!&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/useR2019?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#useR2019&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/q6FsqsDI61&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/q6FsqsDI61&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; useR! 2019 (@UseR2019_Conf) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UseR2019_Conf/status/1150115187430760448?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 13, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;worldwide-dissemination&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. Worldwide dissemination&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone has the time, energy or money to go to UseR!. Some ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/travel/2019/may/22/could-you-give-up-flying-meet-the-no-plane-pioneers&#34;&gt;no fly pioneers&lt;/a&gt;’ have given up flying to support global efforts to tackle the climate crisis. I was very impressed to see acknowledgement of the conference’s climate impacts, with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://enquetes.inra.fr/index.php/136679?lang=en&#34;&gt;form&lt;/a&gt; used to help calculate its carbon impact:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2019-07-13-great-things-user2019_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the reason, it is certain that the contents of UseR! will be of great interest to many more people than the ~2000 people who attended in person. By recording and (eventually) releasing the videos of the talk, a much larger audience, into the millions, can be reached, as highlighted on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://user2019.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All talks will be recorded and all keynote sessions will be live streamed. Everything will be made available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_R5smHVXRYGhZYDJsnXTwg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R Consortium YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to R Consortium for supporting that initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, UseRs are excellent communicators, as can be seen from a quick glance at the buzzing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/user2019?lang=en-gb&#34;&gt;#UseR2019 hashtag&lt;/a&gt;, three of which are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Dear everyone at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/useR2019?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#useR2019&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;br&gt;We thank you very much for your R-enthusiasm 😃.&lt;br&gt;We hope that you as much fun as we had😋.&lt;br&gt;See you in Saint-Louis next year for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/useR2020?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#useR2020&lt;/a&gt;! 🇫🇷🔜🇺🇸&lt;br&gt;On vous aime !&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; useR! 2019 (@UseR2019_Conf) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UseR2019_Conf/status/1149790615963615232?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 12, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;MASSIVE thank you 🙏🌟💜🌍 to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HeathrTurnr?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@HeathrTurnr&lt;/a&gt; for her AMAZING and continued championing of making the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; community so diverse and welcoming, for all from work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/useR?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#useR&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RLadies?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#RLadies&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LatinR?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#LatinR&lt;/a&gt; and more. We owe a lot to Heather’s hard work &amp;amp; dedication 🏆 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/useR2019?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#useR2019&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Aisw11SKjc&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Aisw11SKjc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alice Data (@alice_data) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alice_data/status/1149680375817494529?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 12, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;vroom &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; 📦, because life is too short to read slow! 🏎️💨&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;slides 📽️ from my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/useR2019?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#useR2019&lt;/a&gt; talk available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/3h6b2m7lQO&#34;&gt;https://t.co/3h6b2m7lQO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jim Hester (@jimhester_) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jimhester_/status/1149651592884285441?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 12, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increasing proportion of content now available online, nearing 100% notwithstanding socials, raises the prospect of making future conferences more environmentally sustainable by encouraging remote participation. This could model the 2019 &lt;a href=&#34;https://stay-grounded.org/conference/&#34;&gt;Stay Grounded conference in Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;, which was a “flight free conference”. I discussed the idea of having a single host location with Martin Maechler on the train journey home. This could involve the local organisers and people living nearby attending in person, and then allowing others to attend remotely via live streaming, perhaps in national ‘conference hubs’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;relaxed-atmosphere&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;3. Relaxed atmosphere&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about UseR! 2019 was less objective but equally important: the social atmosphere. The most reason why it had such a good vibe, I guess, was the attendees: in my experience R users, and people involved in the open source community in general, tend to friendly, humble and team-orientated. Of course, this is how conferences should be. Many are, but I couldn’t help notice a contrast between the humility of the ‘big names’ in the R community and the sense of self importance that some high profile academics have in some disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UseRs seem to have a great sense of humour and don’t take themselves too seriously, which contributed to a friendly, inviting and non-hierarchical atmosphere. This friendliness is self organising, but is also built into the constitution of UseR! in its &lt;a href=&#34;http://user2019.r-project.org/coc/&#34;&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt;. Take note future conference organisers: it’s easy to add a CoC and +s of doing so could be great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final reason for the relaxed atmosphere I noticed was more objective: all the equipment worked well, session chairs were well briefed on what they needed to and when, there were floating mics to allow clear questions from the audience, and the rooms were large enough such that at no point did I feel crammed into a session. Furthermore, the arrangement and audio system of the rooms made it feel easy to change session, in case there were two talks in parallel sessions you really wanted to see. Again, hats off to the organisers: it was VERY well organised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-host-city-of-toulouse&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4. The host city of Toulouse&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked the host city but, due to recent University of Leeds regulations blocking AirBnB, I had to change accommodation plans at late notice. This involved a ~3km trek out to the West of the city. Instead of spending 2 hours each day walking there and back, I decided to hire a bike. To my surprise, the system just worked: I typed in some details in the nearest bike hire station I could find and had my own wheels for the week (which looked like those in the photo below). All for the bargain price of €5 for the week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.ladepeche.fr/api/v1/images/view/5c34e8ca8fe56f09063e1f8f/large/image.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;blockquote class=&#34;instagram-media&#34; data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-permalink=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/p/BtvyxGfIf9L/&#34; data-instgrm-version=&#34;12&#34; style=&#34; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&#34;&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;padding:16px;&#34;&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/p/BtvyxGfIf9L/&#34; style=&#34; background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;&#34;&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;&#34;&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;padding: 19% 0;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;&#34;&gt;&lt;svg width=&#34;50px&#34; height=&#34;50px&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 60 60&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; xmlns=&#34;https://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34; xmlns:xlink=&#34;https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&#34;&gt;&lt;g stroke=&#34;none&#34; stroke-width=&#34;1&#34; fill=&#34;none&#34; fill-rule=&#34;evenodd&#34;&gt;&lt;g transform=&#34;translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)&#34; fill=&#34;#000000&#34;&gt;&lt;g&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;padding-top: 8px;&#34;&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;&#34;&gt; View this post on Instagram&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;padding: 12.5% 0;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;margin-left: 8px;&#34;&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;margin-left: auto;&#34;&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&#34; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;p style=&#34; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&#34;&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/p/BtvyxGfIf9L/&#34; style=&#34; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Commencez la semaine avec VélÔToulouse pour faciliter vos trajets ! 😎 🚲 #velotoulouse #toulousemaville #bikelife #toulouse Belle semaine à tous ☀️ Thank you @viktoriia_naumi for your picture 🙂&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&#34; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&#34;&gt;A post shared by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/velotoulouse31000/&#34; style=&#34; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; VélÔToulouse Officiel&lt;/a&gt; (@velotoulouse31000) on &lt;time style=&#34; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&#34; datetime=&#34;2019-02-11T15:36:54+00:00&#34;&gt;Feb 11, 2019 at 7:36am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed to find time to go running on two of the mornings, making me realise how car-dominated Toulouse, like many other cities, is. The car dominated nature of the city is shown in the images below, which show my running route that dodged giant roads, and a photo of one of the main roads, which was not particularly friendly to people walking and cycling to say the least!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/48247285282/in/photostream/&#34; title=&#34;Screenshot_2019-07-10-06-53-00-088_net.osmand.plus&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48247285282_21b35c313b_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;800&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot_2019-07-10-06-53-00-088_net.osmand.plus&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/48247197386/in/photostream/&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20190710_063516&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48247197386_391eb748b5_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20190710_063516&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the car traffic, the cycleways in Toulouse were great. I recommend anyone visiting a city for a few days to get a bike, a great way to see the city close up, and get from A to B efficiently, avoiding traffic congestion and with the freedom to get off the beaten (road) track. For fun, I recorded some of my routes in Toulouse and uploaded them to OSM, the free and open access community made global mapping database (which I fully endorse over Google Maps ;), allowing reproducible code to show my everyday trip to the conference and back:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;download.file(&amp;quot;https://www.openstreetmap.org/trace/3046619/data&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;track1.gpx&amp;quot;)
sf::st_layers(&amp;quot;track1.gpx&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Driver: GPX 
## Available layers:
##     layer_name     geometry_type features fields
## 1    waypoints             Point        0     23
## 2       routes       Line String        0     12
## 3       tracks Multi Line String        1     12
## 4 route_points             Point        0     25
## 5 track_points             Point      152     27&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;track = sf::read_sf(&amp;quot;track1.gpx&amp;quot;, layer = &amp;quot;tracks&amp;quot;)
mapview::mapview(track)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:672px;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;leaflet html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;minZoom&#34;:1,&#34;maxZoom&#34;:100,&#34;crs&#34;:{&#34;crsClass&#34;:&#34;L.CRS.EPSG3857&#34;,&#34;code&#34;:null,&#34;proj4def&#34;:null,&#34;projectedBounds&#34;:null,&#34;options&#34;:{}},&#34;preferCanvas&#34;:false,&#34;bounceAtZoomLimits&#34;:false,&#34;maxBounds&#34;:[[[-90,-370]],[[90,370]]]},&#34;calls&#34;:[{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;CartoDB.Positron&#34;,1,&#34;CartoDB.Positron&#34;,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;CartoDB.DarkMatter&#34;,2,&#34;CartoDB.DarkMatter&#34;,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;OpenStreetMap&#34;,3,&#34;OpenStreetMap&#34;,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;Esri.WorldImagery&#34;,4,&#34;Esri.WorldImagery&#34;,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;OpenTopoMap&#34;,5,&#34;OpenTopoMap&#34;,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;createMapPane&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;line&#34;,430]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addPolylines&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[[[[{&#34;lng&#34;:[1.400506,1.4006889,1.4007832,1.400683,1.4006602,1.4005251,1.400484,1.4005088,1.4007603,1.4010393,1.401267,1.4014611,1.4018177,1.4021275,1.4025796,1.4029969,1.4036092,1.4039726,1.4043514,1.4046799,1.4049264,1.4051744,1.4054378,1.4056694,1.4059087,1.4061291,1.4063419,1.4065754,1.4068117,1.4070478,1.4071941,1.4072091,1.4072379,1.4073143,1.4073843,1.4074604,1.4075272,1.4076321,1.4078188,1.4080745,1.4083397,1.4086052,1.4088915,1.4091065,1.409369,1.4097115,1.4101483,1.4106225,1.4110997,1.4111954,1.4109534,1.4109835,1.411223,1.4115138,1.4118245,1.4121433,1.4124222,1.4127341,1.4130401,1.4128176,1.4126221,1.4124203,1.4121979,1.4125378,1.4127518,1.41298,1.4135993,1.413874,1.4140961,1.4143976,1.4148247,1.4151264,1.4153615,1.4156107,1.4158784,1.4161339,1.4165603,1.4168287,1.4171691,1.4174351,1.4177088,1.417982,1.4182537,1.4185344,1.419263,1.4195111,1.4197766,1.4200856,1.4204674,1.4208365,1.4211473,1.4215132,1.4217384,1.4220957,1.4225408,1.4228799,1.4230849,1.4234496,1.4237093,1.4238463,1.4239208,1.4238005,1.4236883,1.4239385,1.4242242,1.4245101,1.4247684,1.4250772,1.4253445,1.4255234,1.4257759,1.4259649,1.4261808,1.426402,1.4266341,1.4268318,1.4270289,1.4272602,1.427444,1.4277168,1.4279732,1.4282314,1.428482,1.4287865,1.4290637,1.4293718,1.4296592,1.4300627,1.4304569,1.430709,1.4311231,1.4314097,1.4317594,1.4319881,1.432236,1.4324832,1.4327659,1.433001,1.4331084,1.433165,1.4331345,1.4331961,1.4333423,1.4334665,1.4335608,1.4337393,1.4340082,1.434249,1.4344912,1.4347306,1.4349818,1.4349452],&#34;lat&#34;:[43.6057735,43.6054551,43.6052884,43.6054591,43.6056613,43.6059605,43.6061691,43.6063873,43.6063477,43.6061643,43.606021,43.6058989,43.6057571,43.6056363,43.6054479,43.6052723,43.6050985,43.6048724,43.6046683,43.6044945,43.6045481,43.6044707,43.6043981,43.6042952,43.6042107,43.6041141,43.6040063,43.6038925,43.6038023,43.6039354,43.6042589,43.6045611,43.604811,43.6051093,43.6053569,43.6056185,43.6058346,43.6060314,43.6062175,43.6063931,43.6065538,43.6067143,43.6069352,43.607101,43.6072562,43.6074517,43.6076036,43.6077986,43.6079583,43.6081255,43.6082053,43.6083839,43.6084973,43.6086482,43.6087966,43.6089424,43.6090696,43.6092024,43.6093297,43.6094365,43.6095728,43.6097072,43.6098247,43.6097834,43.6096694,43.6095187,43.609333,43.6094028,43.6095258,43.6096657,43.6097886,43.6097975,43.6098744,43.6099695,43.6100222,43.6100764,43.6101649,43.6101938,43.6102833,43.6102942,43.6103424,43.6103936,43.6103947,43.6103537,43.6101626,43.610038,43.6099459,43.6098048,43.609652,43.609526,43.6094204,43.6093219,43.6092126,43.6091031,43.6089466,43.6088313,43.6086773,43.6085818,43.6085224,43.6086867,43.6088689,43.6090299,43.6091929,43.6093412,43.6094855,43.6096801,43.6098381,43.610032,43.610028,43.6098624,43.6096618,43.6094755,43.6092891,43.6090951,43.6088907,43.6087302,43.608556,43.6083525,43.6081587,43.6081203,43.6082041,43.6082101,43.6082597,43.6083702,43.6084624,43.6085817,43.6087528,43.6088219,43.6089356,43.6089602,43.6091512,43.6092884,43.6094538,43.6095247,43.6096219,43.6096969,43.6097306,43.6098208,43.6099845,43.6101808,43.6104616,43.6106517,43.6108931,43.6110814,43.6112491,43.6113794,43.6114408,43.6115166,43.6115946,43.6116463,43.6116963,43.6115106]}]]],null,&#34;track&#34;,{&#34;crs&#34;:{&#34;crsClass&#34;:&#34;L.CRS.EPSG3857&#34;,&#34;code&#34;:null,&#34;proj4def&#34;:null,&#34;projectedBounds&#34;:null,&#34;options&#34;:{}},&#34;pane&#34;:&#34;line&#34;,&#34;stroke&#34;:true,&#34;color&#34;:&#34;#6666FF&#34;,&#34;weight&#34;:2,&#34;opacity&#34;:0.9,&#34;fill&#34;:false,&#34;fillColor&#34;:&#34;#6666FF&#34;,&#34;fillOpacity&#34;:1,&#34;smoothFactor&#34;:1,&#34;noClip&#34;:false},&#34;&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;link rel=\&#34;stylesheet\&#34; type=\&#34;text/css\&#34; href=\&#34;lib/popup/popup.css\&#34;&gt;&lt;\/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;div class=\&#34;scrollableContainer\&#34;&gt;&lt;table class=\&#34;popup scrollable\&#34; id=\&#34;popup\&#34;&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;coord&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Feature ID&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;1&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;alt&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;name&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;cmt&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;alt&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;3&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;desc&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;src&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;alt&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;5&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;link1_href&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;6&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;link1_text&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;alt&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;7&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;link1_type&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;8&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;link2_href&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;alt&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;9&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;link2_text&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;10&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;link2_type&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;alt&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;11&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;number&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;12&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;type&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;NA&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr class=&#39;alt&#39;&gt;&lt;td&gt;13&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;geometry&amp;emsp;&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td align=&#39;right&#39;&gt;sfc_MULTILINESTRING&amp;emsp;&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;\/table&gt;&lt;\/div&gt;&lt;\/body&gt;&lt;\/html&gt;&#34;,{&#34;maxWidth&#34;:800,&#34;minWidth&#34;:50,&#34;autoPan&#34;:true,&#34;keepInView&#34;:false,&#34;closeButton&#34;:true,&#34;closeOnClick&#34;:true,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;&#34;},&#34;1&#34;,{&#34;interactive&#34;:false,&#34;permanent&#34;:false,&#34;direction&#34;:&#34;auto&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;offset&#34;:[0,0],&#34;textsize&#34;:&#34;10px&#34;,&#34;textOnly&#34;:false,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;sticky&#34;:true},{&#34;stroke&#34;:true,&#34;weight&#34;:3,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;fill&#34;:false,&#34;fillOpacity&#34;:0,&#34;bringToFront&#34;:false,&#34;sendToBack&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addScaleBar&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[{&#34;maxWidth&#34;:100,&#34;metric&#34;:true,&#34;imperial&#34;:true,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:true,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;bottomleft&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addHomeButton&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[1.400484,43.6038023,1.4349818,43.6116963,&#34;Zoom to track&#34;,&#34;&lt;strong&gt; track &lt;\/strong&gt;&#34;,&#34;bottomright&#34;]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addLayersControl&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[[&#34;CartoDB.Positron&#34;,&#34;CartoDB.DarkMatter&#34;,&#34;OpenStreetMap&#34;,&#34;Esri.WorldImagery&#34;,&#34;OpenTopoMap&#34;],&#34;track&#34;,{&#34;collapsed&#34;:true,&#34;autoZIndex&#34;:true,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;topleft&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addLegend&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[{&#34;colors&#34;:[&#34;#6666FF&#34;],&#34;labels&#34;:[&#34;track&#34;],&#34;na_color&#34;:null,&#34;na_label&#34;:&#34;NA&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;topright&#34;,&#34;type&#34;:&#34;factor&#34;,&#34;title&#34;:&#34;track&#34;,&#34;extra&#34;:null,&#34;layerId&#34;:null,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;info legend&#34;,&#34;group&#34;:&#34;track&#34;}]}],&#34;limits&#34;:{&#34;lat&#34;:[43.6038023,43.6116963],&#34;lng&#34;:[1.400484,1.4349818]}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:{&#34;render&#34;:[{&#34;code&#34;:&#34;function(el, x, data) {\n  return (\n      function(el, x, data) {\n      // get the leaflet map\n      var map = this; //HTMLWidgets.find(&#39;#&#39; + el.id);\n      // we need a new div element because we have to handle\n      // the mouseover output separately\n      // debugger;\n      function addElement () {\n      // generate new div Element\n      var newDiv = $(document.createElement(&#39;div&#39;));\n      // append at end of leaflet htmlwidget container\n      $(el).append(newDiv);\n      //provide ID and style\n      newDiv.addClass(&#39;lnlt&#39;);\n      newDiv.css({\n      &#39;position&#39;: &#39;relative&#39;,\n      &#39;bottomleft&#39;:  &#39;0px&#39;,\n      &#39;background-color&#39;: &#39;rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.7)&#39;,\n      &#39;box-shadow&#39;: &#39;0 0 2px #bbb&#39;,\n      &#39;background-clip&#39;: &#39;padding-box&#39;,\n      &#39;margin&#39;: &#39;0&#39;,\n      &#39;padding-left&#39;: &#39;5px&#39;,\n      &#39;color&#39;: &#39;#333&#39;,\n      &#39;font&#39;: &#39;9px/1.5 \&#34;Helvetica Neue\&#34;, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif&#39;,\n      &#39;z-index&#39;: &#39;700&#39;,\n      });\n      return newDiv;\n      }\n\n\n      // check for already existing lnlt class to not duplicate\n      var lnlt = $(el).find(&#39;.lnlt&#39;);\n\n      if(!lnlt.length) {\n      lnlt = addElement();\n\n      // grab the special div we generated in the beginning\n      // and put the mousmove output there\n\n      map.on(&#39;mousemove&#39;, function (e) {\n      if (e.originalEvent.ctrlKey) {\n      if (document.querySelector(&#39;.lnlt&#39;) === null) lnlt = addElement();\n      lnlt.text(\n                           &#39; lon: &#39; + (e.latlng.lng).toFixed(5) +\n                           &#39; | lat: &#39; + (e.latlng.lat).toFixed(5) +\n                           &#39; | zoom: &#39; + map.getZoom() +\n                           &#39; | x: &#39; + L.CRS.EPSG3857.project(e.latlng).x.toFixed(0) +\n                           &#39; | y: &#39; + L.CRS.EPSG3857.project(e.latlng).y.toFixed(0) +\n                           &#39; | epsg: 3857 &#39; +\n                           &#39; | proj4: +proj=merc +a=6378137 +b=6378137 +lat_ts=0.0 +lon_0=0.0 +x_0=0.0 +y_0=0 +k=1.0 +units=m +nadgrids=@null +no_defs &#39;);\n      } else {\n      if (document.querySelector(&#39;.lnlt&#39;) === null) lnlt = addElement();\n      lnlt.text(\n                      &#39; lon: &#39; + (e.latlng.lng).toFixed(5) +\n                      &#39; | lat: &#39; + (e.latlng.lat).toFixed(5) +\n                      &#39; | zoom: &#39; + map.getZoom() + &#39; &#39;);\n      }\n      });\n\n      // remove the lnlt div when mouse leaves map\n      map.on(&#39;mouseout&#39;, function (e) {\n      var strip = document.querySelector(&#39;.lnlt&#39;);\n      strip.remove();\n      });\n\n      };\n\n      //$(el).keypress(67, function(e) {\n      map.on(&#39;preclick&#39;, function(e) {\n      if (e.originalEvent.ctrlKey) {\n      if (document.querySelector(&#39;.lnlt&#39;) === null) lnlt = addElement();\n      lnlt.text(\n                      &#39; lon: &#39; + (e.latlng.lng).toFixed(5) +\n                      &#39; | lat: &#39; + (e.latlng.lat).toFixed(5) +\n                      &#39; | zoom: &#39; + map.getZoom() + &#39; &#39;);\n      var txt = document.querySelector(&#39;.lnlt&#39;).textContent;\n      console.log(txt);\n      //txt.innerText.focus();\n      //txt.select();\n      setClipboardText(&#39;\&#34;&#39; + txt + &#39;\&#34;&#39;);\n      }\n      });\n\n      //map.on(&#39;click&#39;, function (e) {\n      //  var txt = document.querySelector(&#39;.lnlt&#39;).textContent;\n      //  console.log(txt);\n      //  //txt.innerText.focus();\n      //  //txt.select();\n      //  setClipboardText(txt);\n      //});\n\n      function setClipboardText(text){\n      var id = &#39;mycustom-clipboard-textarea-hidden-id&#39;;\n      var existsTextarea = document.getElementById(id);\n\n      if(!existsTextarea){\n      console.log(&#39;Creating textarea&#39;);\n      var textarea = document.createElement(&#39;textarea&#39;);\n      textarea.id = id;\n      // Place in top-left corner of screen regardless of scroll position.\n      textarea.style.position = &#39;fixed&#39;;\n      textarea.style.top = 0;\n      textarea.style.left = 0;\n\n      // Ensure it has a small width and height. Setting to 1px / 1em\n      // doesn&#39;t work as this gives a negative w/h on some browsers.\n      textarea.style.width = &#39;1px&#39;;\n      textarea.style.height = &#39;1px&#39;;\n\n      // We don&#39;t need padding, reducing the size if it does flash render.\n      textarea.style.padding = 0;\n\n      // Clean up any borders.\n      textarea.style.border = &#39;none&#39;;\n      textarea.style.outline = &#39;none&#39;;\n      textarea.style.boxShadow = &#39;none&#39;;\n\n      // Avoid flash of white box if rendered for any reason.\n      textarea.style.background = &#39;transparent&#39;;\n      document.querySelector(&#39;body&#39;).appendChild(textarea);\n      console.log(&#39;The textarea now exists :)&#39;);\n      existsTextarea = document.getElementById(id);\n      }else{\n      console.log(&#39;The textarea already exists :3&#39;)\n      }\n\n      existsTextarea.value = text;\n      existsTextarea.select();\n\n      try {\n      var status = document.execCommand(&#39;copy&#39;);\n      if(!status){\n      console.error(&#39;Cannot copy text&#39;);\n      }else{\n      console.log(&#39;The text is now on the clipboard&#39;);\n      }\n      } catch (err) {\n      console.log(&#39;Unable to copy.&#39;);\n      }\n      }\n\n\n      }\n      ).call(this.getMap(), el, x, data);\n}&#34;,&#34;data&#34;:null}]}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing this route each day was a great way to clear my head and prepare for my talk on Wednesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;user-2019-socials&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;5. UseR! 2019 socials&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve often heard that the most valuable parts of conferences take place outside the formal sessions and there were ample opportunities for this to happen at UseR! 2019, with plentiful coffee breaks (and plentiful coffee!) and a range of fringe events and social events on a spectrum from the official Gala Dinner to spontaneous social trips to explore the night life in Toulouse. The Gala Dinner was frankly amazing: it’s not everyday that you get to explore and inter nation space station and listen to Flamenco music in the same evening (the photos and video below prove it is possible)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/48256753957/in/photostream/&#34; title=&#34;PANO_20190710_203925.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48256753957_e76846ea55_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;356&#34; alt=&#34;PANO_20190710_203925.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/48256682626/in/album-72157709543796761/&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20190710_201757&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48256682626_35e1995fdb_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20190710_201757&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/48256686546/in/photostream/&#34; title=&#34;VID_20190710_202540&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/31337/48256686546_9048fc1278_h.jpg&#34; width=&#34;1600&#34; height=&#34;900&#34; alt=&#34;VID_20190710_202540&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;meeting-collaborators-and-online-acquaintances&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;6. Meeting collaborators and online acquaintances&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was a great opportunity to catch up with R collaborators. Jakub Nowosad and I did some important thinking on our &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.robinlovelace.net/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geocomputation with R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; open source book (&lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.github.io/user_19/presentation/#1&#34;&gt;see the slides from Jakub’s talk here&lt;/a&gt;), and a photo taken just before the talk below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/48272563561/&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20190712_110533&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48272563561_d2e9a5654b_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20190712_110533&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally managed to persuade Colin Gillespie that we need to update our open source book &lt;a href=&#34;https://csgillespie.github.io/efficientR/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Efficient R Programming&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Watch this space…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met many people whose work I’ve seen online but never had the pleasure of meeting in person, including Timothée Giraud (author of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rCarto/osrm&#34;&gt;osrm&lt;/a&gt; and many other excellent geo* packages), Enrico Spinielli (who is pushing the boundaries of 3d trajectory analysis in R with packages such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/euctrl-pru/trrrj&#34;&gt;trjjj&lt;/a&gt;) and Angela Li (who is pushing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rspatial&#34;&gt;#rspatial&lt;/a&gt; to new levels on the other side of the Atlantic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course there was much serendipity. I had the honour of meeting many of my R heroes, who were all fun and friendly, demonstrating that it is possible to be high flying while humble. On the train back I sat next R Core Team member Martin Meachler, and learned about the messages emitted every time packages such as &lt;code&gt;stplanr&lt;/code&gt;, which depend on packages that use &lt;code&gt;R.oo&lt;/code&gt;, are loaded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(stplanr)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Registered S3 method overwritten by &amp;#39;R.oo&amp;#39;:
##   method        from       
##   throw.default R.methodsS3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in fun(libname, pkgname): rgeos: versions of GEOS runtime 3.7.1-CAPI-1.11.1
## and GEOS at installation 3.7.0-CAPI-1.11.0differ&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got on so well we decided to walk through part of Paris where we both had to change trains as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/48272643002/in/photostream/&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20190712_171219&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48272643002_bda5773a2a_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20190712_171219&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;my-talk&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;My talk&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My talk was part of a session entitled ‘Movement &amp;amp; transport’, that contained the following talks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-2&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;height:auto;&#34; class=&#34;datatables html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-2&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;filter&#34;:&#34;none&#34;,&#34;data&#34;:[[&#34;85&#34;,&#34;87&#34;,&#34;89&#34;,&#34;91&#34;],[&#34;Movement &amp;amp; transport&#34;,&#34;Movement &amp;amp; transport&#34;,&#34;Movement &amp;amp; transport&#34;,&#34;Movement &amp;amp; transport&#34;],[&#34;Rocio Joo&#34;,&#34;Mohammad Mehdi Moradi&#34;,&#34;Christine Thomas-Agnan&#34;,&#34;Robin Lovelace&#34;],[&#34;Navigating through the R packages for movement&#34;,&#34;Classes, methods and data analysis for trajectories&#34;,&#34;Modelling spatial flows with R&#34;,&#34;R for Transport Planning&#34;],[&#34;http://www.user2019.fr/static/pres/t258615.pdf&#34;,&#34;http://www.user2019.fr/static/pres/t251784.pdf&#34;,&#34;http://www.user2019.fr/static/pres/t256726.pdf&#34;,&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/user2019-r-for-transport-planning.html&#34;]],&#34;container&#34;:&#34;&lt;table class=\&#34;display\&#34;&gt;\n  &lt;thead&gt;\n    &lt;tr&gt;\n      &lt;th&gt; &lt;\/th&gt;\n      &lt;th&gt;Session&lt;\/th&gt;\n      &lt;th&gt;Speaker&lt;\/th&gt;\n      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;\/th&gt;\n      &lt;th&gt;link&lt;\/th&gt;\n    &lt;\/tr&gt;\n  &lt;\/thead&gt;\n&lt;\/table&gt;&#34;,&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;order&#34;:[],&#34;autoWidth&#34;:false,&#34;orderClasses&#34;:false,&#34;columnDefs&#34;:[{&#34;orderable&#34;:false,&#34;targets&#34;:0}]}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won’t go into the details of my talk because you can see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/user2019-r-for-transport-planning.html#1&#34;&gt;slides for yourself at the URL&lt;/a&gt;. However, it raised many questions and makes me wonder if it’s worth creating an ‘r-transport’ type organisation. Another question, that I didn’t get to answer, is where should reproducible transport questions go, now that my attempts to create a ‘Transport Planning’ StackExchange site seemed to have failed, as shown in the slide below : ( Any ideas on that, welcome : )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/user2019-r-for-transport-planning.html#28&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!-- The only negative part of the conference for me was that it felt too short. --&gt;
&lt;!-- That&#39;s partly my own fault for  attend fewer conference but give them 100%, rather than attending many and feeling pressed for time. --&gt;
&lt;!-- &#34;Quality over quantity&#34; should be guiding principle of conference attendance I&#39;ve decided. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, UseR! 2019 was a fun, enlightening and inspiring event, and I hope to attend future UseRs, in person or remotely. I wish more conferences were like this. This small write up is designed as a reminder to my future self, and anyone else reading, to remember how good conferences &lt;em&gt;can be&lt;/em&gt;. The example set by this outstanding conference provides some pointers in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geocomputation with R: from inception to physical book</title>
      <link>/presentations/geocompr-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/geocompr-launch/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;lecture-and-book-launch-part-of-leeds-digital-festival&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lecture and book launch, part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://leedsdigitalfestival.org/&#34;&gt;Leeds Digital Festival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk will introduce &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.robinlovelace.net/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geocomputation with R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a new book on R for geographic data that has just been published. Aimed at people new to the subject, I’ll provide some examples to show the power of programming with open source software for high-performance, reproducible mapping and geographic analyis. I will cover a bit of the history but focus on visualisation, which is key to using data to understand the world. Finally, I will provide some pointers for people wanting to get &lt;em&gt;stuck in&lt;/em&gt; and use geocomputation to better understand the world, influence policy and have fun with maps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keynote talk on geocomputation, SatRdays Newcastle</title>
      <link>/presentations/satrday-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/satrday-keynote/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;keynote-talk-at-satrdays-newcastle-https-newcastle2019-satrdays-org-portfolio&#34;&gt;Keynote talk at &lt;a href=&#34;https://newcastle2019.satrdays.org/#portfolio&#34;&gt;SatRdays Newcastle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;geocomputation-with-r-reproducible-geo-workflows-from-getting-data-to-making-maps&#34;&gt;Geocomputation with R: Reproducible Geo* workflows, from getting data to making maps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk will introduce &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.robinlovelace.net/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geocomputation with R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a new book on R for geographic data.
It will demonstrate how far R has evolved as an environment for geographic data analysis and visualisation, and provide a taster of what is in the book and, more importantly, what is possible when &amp;lsquo;data science&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;GIS&amp;rsquo; meet.
With new packages such as &lt;strong&gt;sf&lt;/strong&gt;, geographic data analysis has become more accessible.
The talk will show how geographic analysis can bring local examples to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;r-packages&#34;&gt;R packages:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/r-spatial/sf&#34;&gt;sf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.github.io/stplanr/&#34;&gt;stplanr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>stplanr paper published</title>
      <link>/2019/02/25/sustainable-transport-planning-with-r-stplanr-paper-published/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/25/sustainable-transport-planning-with-r-stplanr-paper-published/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I am very happy to announce that the paper &lt;em&gt;stplanr: A package for transport planning&lt;/em&gt; has been published in The R Journal &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Lovelace and Ellison 2018)&lt;/span&gt; 🎉.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the result of around 3 years of work: it took us (co-author &lt;a href=&#34;https://business.sydney.edu.au/staff/richard.ellison&#34;&gt;Richard Ellison&lt;/a&gt; and me) over a year to get round to writing the paper after the &lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt; package was first released on &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/package=stplanr&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt; in November 2015 (see its &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/src/contrib/Archive/stplanr/&#34;&gt;archive on CRAN&lt;/a&gt; for details); it wasn’t until March 2017 that the paper was formally submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, it was in the review process for almost 2 years, before finally being published last week.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Confusingly, the paper has an official publication date of 2018, despite the second volume of The R Journal in 2018 actually being finished in 2019! See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2018-1/&#34;&gt;current issue&lt;/a&gt; of The R Journal for all papers in this second 2018 volume. There are some interesting papers in there, not least an explanation of methods for visualising point density by &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Evangelista and Beskow (2018)&lt;/span&gt;, and an explanation of &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; pipe &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Mount and Zumel 2018)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of going into the details of what the paper says (see the nicely formatted &lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2018/RJ-2018-053/RJ-2018-053.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt; for that), I’d like to finish this post by saying a big THANK YOU to the editorial team behind The R Journal for such a high standard (better than many expensive journals I might add, The R Journal is volunteer-run to the best of my knowledge), especially Roger Bivand and John Verzani.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plans are afoot to build on the moment behind &lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt;, which originated as a place to store code that I was using to develop the Propensity to Cycle Tool (PCT, hosted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pct.bike/&#34;&gt;www.pct.bike&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Lovelace et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; and make additional, overdue improvements to the package. For more on that, please head-over to the issue tracker (input welcome) or take a read of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2018/RJ-2018-053/RJ-2018-053.pdf#page=14&#34;&gt;final section&lt;/a&gt; of the just-publised paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-evangelista_geospatial_2018&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evangelista, Paul F., and David Beskow. 2018. “Geospatial Point Density.” &lt;em&gt;The R Journal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-lovelace_stplanr_2018&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, Robin, and Richard Ellison. 2018. “Stplanr: A Package for Transport Planning.” &lt;em&gt;The R Journal&lt;/em&gt; 10 (2): 7–23. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.32614/RJ-2018-053&#34;&gt;10.32614/RJ-2018-053&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-lovelace_propensity_2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, Robin, Anna Goodman, Rachel Aldred, Nikolai Berkoff, Ali Abbas, and James Woodcock. 2017. “The Propensity to Cycle Tool: An Open Source Online System for Sustainable Transport Planning.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Transport and Land Use&lt;/em&gt; 10 (1). doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&#34;&gt;10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-mount_dot-pipe_2018&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mount, John, and Nina Zumel. 2018. “Dot-Pipe: An S3 Extensible Pipe for R.” &lt;em&gt;The R Journal&lt;/em&gt; 10 (2): 309–16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I should say, that it was not the fault of The R Journal’s editorial team that it took so long to publish the paper: I asked for it to be put on hold while I completed the mammoth task of re-writing dozens of functions to support sf (see the pull request in which the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr/pull/198&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sfr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; branch was merged into &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; for the grizzly details).&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aggregating lines, part II</title>
      <link>/2019/02/14/aggregating-lines-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/14/aggregating-lines-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/2018/10/27/aggregating-lines/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated a new method to aggregate overlapping lines. It showed how to combine 2 lines that have an area of overlap. More excitingly, it led to the creation of a new function in &lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;code&gt;overline_sf()&lt;/code&gt;, that lives in the development version of the package. The purpose of this post is to provide an update on the status of the work to refactor the &lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt; function, in a human friendly alternative to discussion in the relevant GitHub issue: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr/issues/273&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr/issues/273&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;set-up&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set-up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To re-cap, these are the package versions we’ll be using in this post (run this line to get the development version of stplanr if you want to reproduce the results):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;ropensci/stplanr&amp;quot;, ref = &amp;quot;refactor-overline&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The library is loaded and the input data from the previous post was loaded as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(stplanr)
routes_fast_sf$value = 1
sl = routes_fast_sf[2:3, ]
sl$value = c(2, 5)
overline_sf2 = function(sl, attrib) {
  attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;
  attrib1 = paste0(attrib, &amp;quot;.1&amp;quot;)
  sl_intersection = sf::st_intersection(sl[1, attrib], sl[2, attrib])
  sl_intersection[[attrib]] = sl_intersection[[attrib]] + sl_intersection[[attrib1]]
  sl_intersection[[attrib1]] = NULL
  sl_seg = sf::st_difference(sl[attrib], sf::st_geometry(sl_intersection))
  rnet = rbind(sl_intersection, sl_seg)
  return(rnet)
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was used as the basis of a demonstration of how overline works, demonstrated in the following code chunk and resulting plot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rnet = overline_sf(sl, &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;)
plot(rnet[&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;], lwd = rnet$value)
plot(sl[&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;], lwd = sl$value, col = sf::sf.colors(2, alpha = 0.5))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;dealing-with-many-lines&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dealing with many lines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above method worked with 2 lines but how can it be used to process many lines? Clearly the same function could be implemented on another line, but it would need to work from the 3 lines of the newly created &lt;code&gt;rnet&lt;/code&gt; object rather than the original 2 routes. Let’s introduce a 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; route into the equation, that does not intersect with this newly created &lt;strong&gt;rnet&lt;/strong&gt; object:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl3 = routes_fast_sf[4, ]
rnet = overline_sf2(rnet, sl)
plot(rnet$geometry, lwd = rnet$value)
plot(sl3, col = &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;, add = TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case the method of adding to rnet is simple: just add the entirety of the line to the &lt;code&gt;rnet&lt;/code&gt; object:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;
rnet3 = rbind(rnet, sl3[attrib])
plot(rnet3$geometry, lwd = rnet3$value)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works fine. In fact it works better than the original &lt;code&gt;overline&lt;/code&gt; function because it does not add the value of the existing thickest line in the previous figure onto the new line, a problem associated with &lt;code&gt;overline.sp()&lt;/code&gt; that is illustrated in the following code chunk and resulting figure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl1_3 = as(routes_fast_sf[2:4, ], &amp;quot;Spatial&amp;quot;)
rnet3_sp = overline(sl1_3, attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;)
plot(rnet3_sp, lwd = rnet3_sp$value)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A question that arises from the previous example is this: what if the next line intersects with the route network? It is no longer possible to simply add together two values. This can be illustrated by introducing 2 more lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl4_5 = routes_fast_sf[5:6, ]
plot(rnet3$geometry, lwd = rnet3$value)
plot(sl4_5$geometry, col = &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;, add = TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the new lines intersect with the newest part of the route network. This means that we cannot simply &lt;code&gt;rbind()&lt;/code&gt; them to it as we did for &lt;code&gt;sl3&lt;/code&gt;. They need to be dealt with separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we deal with them, it’s worth taking some time to consider what we mean by ‘intersect’. Intersection is actuall a specific type of geometric relation between 2 sets of features. We can see the type of relation by using the function &lt;code&gt;st_relate()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;relations = sf::st_relate(sl4_5, rnet3)
relations
unique(as.vector(relations))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows us something important: although 2 elements (1 and 4) of &lt;code&gt;rnet&lt;/code&gt; relate &lt;em&gt;in some way&lt;/em&gt; to the new lines, only the 4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; feature has a linear, overlapping relation with it. That relation is &lt;code&gt;1F1F00102&lt;/code&gt; which, as far as I can tell, is not a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DE-9IM#Spatial_predicates&#34;&gt;named spatial predicate&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;FF1F00102&lt;/code&gt; means ‘intersects and touches’ but does not have a linear overlap). This relation is what we need to decide whether or not to simply bind a new feature to the growing &lt;code&gt;rnet&lt;/code&gt;, whether we need to break it up (or at least part of it) into smaller lines before doing so (it also raises the wider question of which order should we do things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the simple case of &lt;em&gt;whether&lt;/em&gt; to simply bind the next line (4) onto &lt;code&gt;rnet3&lt;/code&gt; the answer is simple now we know the string code associated with linear overlaps. First we’ll test it on the previous example of &lt;code&gt;sl3&lt;/code&gt; and the original &lt;code&gt;rnet&lt;/code&gt; composed of 3 features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;relate_rnet_3 = sf::st_relate(rnet, sl3, pattern = &amp;quot;1F1F00102&amp;quot;)
relate_rnet_3
any(lengths(relate_rnet_3))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;FALSE&lt;/code&gt; meant there was no linear overlaps. So we simply used &lt;code&gt;rbind()&lt;/code&gt;. When we ask the same question of &lt;code&gt;rnet3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sl4&lt;/code&gt;, however, the answer is &lt;code&gt;TRUE&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl4 = sl4_5[1, ]
relate_rnet_4 = sf::st_relate(rnet3, sl4, pattern = &amp;quot;1F1F00102&amp;quot;)
relate_rnet_4
any(lengths(relate_rnet_4))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to proceed? We need to avoid &lt;code&gt;rnet&lt;/code&gt; objects containing any overlapping lines. Because &lt;code&gt;sl4&lt;/code&gt; overlaps with part of &lt;code&gt;rnet3&lt;/code&gt; we will need to remove the overlapping line, run the &lt;code&gt;overline_sf2()&lt;/code&gt; function, and then re-combine the result with the pre-existing route network object. We can split-up the &lt;code&gt;rnet3&lt;/code&gt; object into overlapping and non-overlapping features as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sel_overlaps = lengths(relate_rnet_4) &amp;gt; 0
rnet_overlaps = rnet3[sel_overlaps, ]
rnet3_tmp = rnet3[!sel_overlaps, ]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can check that there is only one overlapping feature as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nrow(rnet_overlaps)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we can proceed to join the two features together using our new function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rnet_overlaps4 = overline_sf2(rbind(rnet_overlaps, sl4[attrib]))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding this back to the &lt;code&gt;rnet3&lt;/code&gt; object results in an larger &lt;code&gt;rnet&lt;/code&gt; object incorporating all the &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;geometry&lt;/code&gt; column data we have so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rnet = rbind(rnet3_tmp, rnet_overlaps4)
plot(rnet$geometry, lwd = rnet$value)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information provided so far informed the creation of the following function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stplanr::overline_sf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This function made use of the slightly simpler individual route-joining function, and associated helper functions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stplanr::overline_sf2

stplanr::overlaps
stplanr::to_linestring&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from being clunky, this approach has the additional flaw of not working. It works fine for lines 2 to 6 in &lt;code&gt;routes_fast_sf&lt;/code&gt;, as illustrated below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;r6 = routes_fast_sf[2:6, ]
rnet6 = overline_sf(r6, attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;)
plot(rnet6)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A problem arises when we try to run the same command on the same data, but with one more line added. That will be the topic of the next post on aggregating lines to form route networks, which will also introduce a new function &lt;code&gt;overline2()&lt;/code&gt;, developed by my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;https://environment.leeds.ac.uk/transport/staff/964/dr-malcolm-morgan&#34;&gt;Malcolm Morgan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;another-benchmark&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Another benchmark&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide a taster of the new function, let’s see it in action in a benchmark on this latest route network consisting of the five lines illustrated in the previous plot. Again, we use &lt;code&gt;bench::mark()&lt;/code&gt; to benchmark each approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bench::mark(check = FALSE,
  overline = stplanr::overline(r6, &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;),
  overline_sf = stplanr::overline_sf(r6, &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;),
  overline2 = stplanr::overline2(r6, &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;)
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again the results are not Earth-shattering and should be taken with a large pinch of salt: performance should not be evaluated against these relatively tiny datasets, but against the scale of datasets that the functions were designed to handle: city scale route networks involving thousands of overlapping lines. The same principle is used in the benchmarking section of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://h2oai.github.io/db-benchmark/&#34;&gt;h2oai website&lt;/a&gt;: focus on benchmarks that apply to the datasets you will actually be using. In this case, my hypothesis is that the geometric functions &lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;overline_sf()&lt;/code&gt; will perform disproportionately badly as the size of the input dataset grows (to be tested). Still, it is interesting to note that the new &lt;code&gt;overline2()&lt;/code&gt; function uses way more memory than the other functions. More next time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geocomputation with R: Empower yourself with geo data</title>
      <link>/presentations/nurd-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/nurd-keynote/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;keynote-lecture-for-the-northwest-universities-r-day-manchester&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Keynote lecture for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/NWURday?src=hash&#34;&gt;Northwest Universities R Day&lt;/a&gt;, Manchester&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this, titled &lt;em&gt;Geocomputation with R: Empower yourself with free software and geo&lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; data&lt;/em&gt;, I provide an overview of the evolving landscape for working with geographic data using open source, command-line driven software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/nurd.html#1&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/nurd.ogg&#34;&gt;Audio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aggregating lines, Part I</title>
      <link>/2018/10/27/aggregating-lines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/27/aggregating-lines/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been a busy 12 months but with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.robinlovelace.net/&#34;&gt;Geocomputation with R&lt;/a&gt; book nearing completion&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’ve finally found some time to update my blog and do a bit of thinking, about the tangled topic of line aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-aggregate-lines&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why aggregate lines?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transport ‘flow’ on any particular segment of the transport networks is the aggregate (sum) of trips that pass through it &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Hollander 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. Finding the flow across a transport network based on input data composed of individual routes, is therefore an aggregation problem. It requires a more complex solution than that provided by the &lt;code&gt;aggregate()&lt;/code&gt; function in the base R &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(R Core Team 2018)&lt;/span&gt; package &lt;strong&gt;stats&lt;/strong&gt;, however, because the geometry of the output &lt;code&gt;LINESTRING&lt;/code&gt;s will be fundamentally different than the input &lt;code&gt;LINESTRINGS&lt;/code&gt; of the routes: a route network is composed of many small way segments, but a route is a single long &lt;code&gt;LINESTRING&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aggregating-lines-with-overline-mki&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aggregating lines with overline() MKI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating such a route network, with aggregated values per segment, is the problem that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.github.io/stplanr/reference/overline.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; function in the R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was designed to solve (see a 3.5 yr-old question on &lt;a href=&#34;https://gis.stackexchange.com/questions/139681/overlaying-lines-and-aggregating-their-values-for-overlapping-segments&#34;&gt;gis.stackexchange.com&lt;/a&gt; for more context).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function works well and is the basis of the Route Network layer (MSOA) in the Propensity to Cycle Tool (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pct.bike/&#34;&gt;PCT&lt;/a&gt;). In fact it was developed precisely for this purpose, as illustrated in the image below, which shows a common visualization/analysis problem encountered by transport researchers when working with multiple routes: overlapping routes are not easy to identify from non-overlapping routes: notice the red lines in the centre of Leeds in the image look the same as the red lines on the outskirts, despite representing much more movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-2&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/npct/pct-team/master/figures/early.png&#34; alt=&#34;Demonstration of the need for line aggregation from a very early version of the Propensity to Cycle Tool, developed at the &#39;Hack my Route&#39; data dive at [ODI Leeds](https://twitter.com/search?q=%23hackmyroute&amp;amp;src=typd).&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Demonstration of the need for line aggregation from a very early version of the Propensity to Cycle Tool, developed at the ‘Hack my Route’ data dive at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23hackmyroute&amp;amp;src=typd&#34;&gt;ODI Leeds&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To overcome the problem &lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt; was born (credit to Barry Rowlingson who wrote the foundations of the function), and it works (on a tiny dataset of 2 lines) as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(stplanr)
sl_sp = routes_fast[2:3, ]
sl_sp@data = data.frame(value = c(2, 5))
plot(sl_sp, lwd = 9, col = &amp;quot;yellow&amp;quot;)
rnet_sp = overline(sl_sp, attr = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;)
plot(rnet_sp, add = TRUE, lwd = rnet_sp$value)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2018-10-27-aggregating-lines_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Illustration of the overline() function for line aggregation in action on a tiny example dataset. Note the left-most line is wider than the two lines that feed into it, demonstrating how line aggregation can be used to estimate flow on a road network.&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 2: Illustration of the overline() function for line aggregation in action on a tiny example dataset. Note the left-most line is wider than the two lines that feed into it, demonstrating how line aggregation can be used to estimate flow on a road network.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The utility of such a function is illustrated in the figure below, which shows the original route network layer of the PCT in action over a similar area of Leeds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-4&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/npct/pct-team/master/figures/fastest-net-headingly.png&#34; alt=&#34;Early version of the route network layer in the Propensity to Cycle Tool.&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 3: Early version of the route network layer in the Propensity to Cycle Tool.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works great and the resulting network is used for strategic network planning: you can download route network data in the ‘Region data’ tab of the PCT &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Lovelace et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt;. The route network data for Leeds can, for example, be downloaded as a &lt;code&gt;.geojson&lt;/code&gt; file from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct-outputs-regional-notR/raw/master/commute/msoa/west-yorkshire/rnet.geojson&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are some issues: the function works on the older &lt;code&gt;SpatialLinesDataFrame&lt;/code&gt; class defined in the &lt;strong&gt;sp&lt;/strong&gt; package &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(&lt;span class=&#34;citeproc-not-found&#34; data-reference-id=&#34;pebesma_simple_2018&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. This data class has been superseded by the simpler &lt;code&gt;sf&lt;/code&gt; class in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/r-spatial/sf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package, which is faster than &lt;strong&gt;sp&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ATFutures/geobench&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; (if not many) operations. Another issue with &lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt; is that in some cases when 2 lines meet, the resulting aggregated line can be longer than it should be. So there are performance and functionality issues to address. Rather than solve them all here, this post sets-out the issue using reproducible code and suggests next steps for a new &lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt; function (or perhaps just an updated &lt;code&gt;overline.sf()&lt;/code&gt; function which currently just wraps &lt;code&gt;overline.sp()&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aggregating-lines-with-sf&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aggregating lines with sf&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather that starting from scratch and writing a geographic algorithm from the ground-up, we will start by exploring solutions provided by existing packages, notably &lt;strong&gt;sf&lt;/strong&gt;, which provides an interface to the &lt;code&gt;GEOS&lt;/code&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start simple, with just 2 lines, which have an associated amount of flow (with illustrative values of 2 and 5 in this case):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(stplanr)
sl = routes_fast_sf[2:3, ]
sl$value = c(2, 5)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These lines clearly have a decent amount of overlap, which can be extracted using the function &lt;code&gt;st_intersection()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl_intersection = sf::st_intersection(sl[1, ], sl[2, ])
plot(sl$geometry, lwd = 9, col = sf::sf.colors(2, alpha = 0.5))
plot(sl_intersection, add = TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-6&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2018-10-27-aggregating-lines_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Illustration of the results of st_intersection&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 4: Illustration of the results of st_intersection
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we can find the aggregated value associated with this new segment as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl_intersection$value = sum(sl_intersection$value, sl_intersection$value.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still do not have a full route network composed of 3 non-overlapping lines, however: the original lines need to be ‘clipped’ so that they do not overlap with &lt;code&gt;sl_intersection&lt;/code&gt;. This can be done as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl_seg1 = sf::st_difference(sl[1, ], sl_intersection)
sl_seg2 = sf::st_difference(sl[2, ], sl_intersection)
plot(sl$geometry, lwd = 9, col = sf::sf.colors(2, alpha = 0.5))
plot(sl_seg1, add = TRUE)
plot(sl_seg2, add = TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2018-10-27-aggregating-lines_files/figure-html/Demonstration%20of%20%60st_difference()%60.-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have all the geographic components needed for a route network. The only remaining task is to combine them, using &lt;code&gt;rbind&lt;/code&gt;, right? Not quite: the following command fails:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rnet = rbind(sl_seg1, sl_seg2, sl_intersection)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Error in rbind.data.frame(...): numbers of columns of arguments do not match&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson: we need to be more careful in isolating the value to aggregate. We will therefore run the previous stages again, but with &lt;code&gt;attrib&lt;/code&gt; set to the attribute we would like to aggregate over (&lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; in this case):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;
attrib1 = paste0(attrib, &amp;quot;.1&amp;quot;)
sl_intersection = sf::st_intersection(sl[1, attrib], sl[2, attrib])
sl_intersection[[attrib]] = sl_intersection[[attrib]] + sl_intersection[[attrib1]]
sl_intersection[[attrib1]] = NULL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leaves us with a ‘clean’ object that only has a value (7) for the attribute column name we want (&lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this basis we can proceed to create the other segments, keeping only the column we’re interested in. To save time and typing, we’ll create both segments in a single command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sl_seg = sf::st_difference(sl[attrib], sf::st_geometry(sl_intersection))
rnet = rbind(sl_intersection, sl_seg)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It worked! Now we’re in a position to plot the resulting route network, with ‘width’ proportional to the flow along each segment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;plot(rnet, lwd = rnet$value)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-11&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2018-10-27-aggregating-lines_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-11-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Illustration of a route network generated with sf functions.&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 5: Illustration of a route network generated with sf functions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-benchmark&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A benchmark&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test that the method is fast, or is at least not slower than the original &lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt; function, at least for this task, we’ll package-up the method in a new function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;overline_sf2 = function(sl, attrib) {
  attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;
  attrib1 = paste0(attrib, &amp;quot;.1&amp;quot;)
  sl_intersection = sf::st_intersection(sl[1, attrib], sl[2, attrib])
  sl_intersection[[attrib]] = sl_intersection[[attrib]] + sl_intersection[[attrib1]]
  sl_intersection[[attrib1]] = NULL
  sl_seg = sf::st_difference(sl[attrib], sf::st_geometry(sl_intersection))
  rnet = rbind(sl_intersection, sl_seg)
  return(rnet)
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to scripts/algorithms/functions, it may be worth taking a look at the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.robinlovelace.net/algorithms.html&#34;&gt;Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; chapter in our near-complete book that teaches a range of geographic methods that use R &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Lovelace, Nowosad, and Muenchow 2019)&lt;/span&gt;. Now the method has been put in a function, we can compare its performance with the per-existing &lt;code&gt;overline()&lt;/code&gt; function for comparison:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bench::mark(check = F,
            overline.sp = overline(sl_sp, attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;),
            overline.sf = overline(sl, attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;),
            overline_sf2 = overline_sf2(sl, attrib = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;)
            )&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 3 x 6
##   expression        min   median `itr/sec` mem_alloc `gc/sec`
##   &amp;lt;bch:expr&amp;gt;   &amp;lt;bch:tm&amp;gt; &amp;lt;bch:tm&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;bch:byt&amp;gt;    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1 overline.sp   12.19ms  12.53ms      79.8  727.76KB     2.05
## 2 overline.sf   16.62ms  17.11ms      58.0    2.32MB     9.28
## 3 overline_sf2   9.34ms   9.51ms     105.    97.62KB     4.20&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are not Earth-shattering: the new function seems to be around the same speed as the original, if a little faster. This is great news, but remember: the new function only works on 2 lines so is much simpler. More work needed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;next-steps&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to generalist this method so it works for many (potentially thousands) of lines in a way that scales, something that should help on the visualization side, a topic that attracts much interest (see for example this &lt;a href=&#34;https://gis.stackexchange.com/questions/778/representation-of-network-flows&#34;&gt;gis.stackexchange post&lt;/a&gt; on the subject and, more broadly, a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://nowosad.github.io/post/maps-distortion/&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; showing how to make animated maps by Jakub Nowosad). There is also work to do on performance but, as Donald Knuth said &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Knuth 1974)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;premature optimization is the root of all evil (or at least most of it) in programming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a more complete &lt;code&gt;overline.sf()&lt;/code&gt; function is needed. That will (hopefully) be the topic of the next blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-hollander_transport_2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hollander, Yaron. 2016. &lt;em&gt;Transport Modelling for a Complete Beginner&lt;/em&gt;. CTthink!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-knuth_computer_1974&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knuth, Donald E. 1974. “Computer Programming as an Art.” &lt;em&gt;Commun. ACM&lt;/em&gt; 17 (12): 667–73. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1145/361604.361612&#34;&gt;10.1145/361604.361612&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-lovelace_propensity_2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, Robin, Anna Goodman, Rachel Aldred, Nikolai Berkoff, Ali Abbas, and James Woodcock. 2017. “The Propensity to Cycle Tool: An Open Source Online System for Sustainable Transport Planning.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Transport and Land Use&lt;/em&gt; 10 (1). doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&#34;&gt;10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-lovelace_geocomputation_2019&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, Robin, Jakub Nowosad, and Jannes Muenchow. 2019. &lt;em&gt;Geocomputation with R&lt;/em&gt;. CRC Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rcoreteam_language_2018&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R Core Team. 2018. &lt;em&gt;R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing&lt;/em&gt;. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Any input on that still welcome - see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.robinlovelace.net/index.html#how-to-contribute&#34;&gt;contributing&lt;/a&gt; section for more.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited lecture: ICTs para la (ciclo)inclusión</title>
      <link>/presentations/icts-inclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/icts-inclusion/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;invited-lecture-in-chile-at-the-seminario-del-transporte-a-la-movilidad-y-accesibilidad-https-m-facebook-com-labcambiarnos-refid-17-in-spanish&#34;&gt;Invited lecture in Chile at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://m.facebook.com/LabCambiarnos/?refid=17&#34;&gt;Seminario del Transporte a la Movilidad y Accesibilidad&lt;/a&gt; (in Spanish)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Title: ICTs para la (ciclo)inclusión&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;pedalea.html#1&#34;&gt;Slides (in Spanish)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Severance, parallels and integration</title>
      <link>/presentations/cycling-and-society-plenary/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/cycling-and-society-plenary/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;plenary-lecture-at-the-cycling-society-conference-bristol&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Plenary lecture at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cyclingandsociety.org/2018programme/&#34;&gt;Cycling &amp;amp; Society conference&lt;/a&gt;, Bristol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk on methods for estimating severance in active transport networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slides: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/cs-infra.html#1&#34;&gt;Severance, parallels and integration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio from the talk is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/cs-infra.ogg&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited seminar: can geographic data save the world?</title>
      <link>/presentations/geocompr-jena/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/geocompr-jena/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;This was the finale of a week of research collaboration and teaching at the Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geographie.uni-jena.de/&#34;&gt;Institut für Geographie&lt;/a&gt;. During the study visit I also worked on &lt;em&gt;Geocomputation with R&lt;/em&gt; with fellow co-author &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geographie.uni-jena.de/en/Chairs/GIScience/Team/M%C3%BCnchow.html&#34;&gt;Jannes Muenchow&lt;/a&gt; and wrote a tutorial on route network analysis in R that can be found at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/geocomp-tranport-workshop&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/geocomp-tranport-workshop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slides: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/robinlovelace/geographic-data-talk/geographic-data-talk.html#1&#34;&gt;Can Geographic Data Save the World?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Geographic Data Save the World?</title>
      <link>/2017/05/02/can-geographic-data-save-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/02/can-geographic-data-save-the-world/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/jquery/jquery.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leafletfix/leafletfix.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4-compressed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/rstudio_leaflet/rstudio_leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-binding/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-providers/leaflet-providers.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;./rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-providers-plugin/leaflet-providers-plugin.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I presented yesterday on the use of geographic data in policy in a flamboyantly named talk: Can geographic data save the world (slides available from &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/RobinLovelace/272796&#34;&gt;rpubs.com/Robinlovelace&lt;/a&gt;). The purpose of this post is to share the slides, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/5x3baro4hrpj57g/gdsl.wav?dl=0&#34;&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt; and some of the ideas resulting from the talk, for the benefit of people interested in the topic but unable to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you just want to sit back and enjoy the slides with audio, rather than read this article, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/5x3baro4hrpj57g/gdsl.wav?dl=0&#34;&gt;click here for the audio&lt;/a&gt; and enjoy the slides below. Otherwise please keep reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://rpubs.com/RobinLovelace/272796&#34; height=&#34;800&#34; width=&#34;1000&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The venue influenced the title. The University of Liverpool’s Geographic Data Science Laboratory (&lt;a href=&#34;https://geographicdatascience.com/&#34;&gt;GDSL&lt;/a&gt;) is a research powerhouse churning out papers close in the field.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-geographic-data-science&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Geographic Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk started with an introduction that defined terms, in which I set-out what I thought made GDS different from its older brother GIS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: `frame_data()` is deprecated, use `tribble()`.
## This warning is displayed once per session.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;tab:unnamed-chunk-2&#34;&gt;Table 1: &lt;/span&gt;Comparison between Geographic Information Systems (GIS) and Geographic Data Science (GDS) research.&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Attribute&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;GIS&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;GDS&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Home disciplines&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Geography&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Geography, Computing, Statistics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Software focus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Graphic User Interface&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Reproduciblility&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Minimal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Maximal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an important distinction to make in the context of having policy impact: by being open and transparent (and therefore using code rather than a non-reproducible Graphical User Interface) geographical research maximises its chances of altering decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple: because if more people can see the data and, crucially, reproduce the results, more people will trust your research and be influenced by it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of clear methods enabled by scripted, reproducible analysis workflow, is even greater in the age of Big Data, which myself and colleagues have defined broadly as “unconventional datasets that are difficult to analyze using established methods” (i.e. those that cannot easily be solved with established products such as Microsoft Excel and ESRI’s ArcMAP) &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Lovelace et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;case-study-the-propensity-to-cycle-tool&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Case study: the Propensity to Cycle Tool&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Propensity to Cycle Tool (PCT) is a good case study highlighting the potential policy impacts of geographical research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly inspired by &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Singleton (2014)&lt;/span&gt; (which was written by a founding member of the GDSL), the PCT provides an open source evidence base highlighting where cycling has the greatest potential to grow. Crucially, the PCT is publicly accessible, meaning that not only transport planning professionals but also members of the public can use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in the cycling potential at the local level in England, or if you are interested in the visualisation of geographic information at multiple levels (area, desire line, route and route network levels in this case), please take a look at the video and have a play at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pct.bike/&#34;&gt;www.pct.bike&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key to the tools’ potential for policy impact is its wide ranging scenarios of change which included Government Target to double cycling by 2025 and a more ambitious Go Dutch scenario in which we cycle as much as the Dutch to, accounting for geographical differences in trip distances and hilliness. The difference between the two scenarios is substantial, as illustrated by the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/raw/master/flow-model/leeds-rnet-gov-go.png&#34; alt=&#34;The Route Network layer illustrating the shifting spatial distribution of cycling flows in Leeds under Government Target (top) and Go Dutch (bottom) scenarios.&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: The Route Network layer illustrating the shifting spatial distribution of cycling flows in Leeds under Government Target (top) and Go Dutch (bottom) scenarios.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed account of the methods (or geographic data science if you like) underlying information on the Propensity to Cycle Tool, I recommend checking out a paper on the subject by myself and other members of the team published in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jtlu.org/index.php/jtlu/article/view/862&#34;&gt;Journal of Transport and Land Use&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Lovelace et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-reproducible-example&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A reproducible example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actions can speak louder than words or, as Linus Torvalds &lt;a href=&#34;https://lkml.org/lkml/2000/8/25/132&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk is cheap. Show me the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that basis, to show what I meant by reproducibility and ‘data carpentry’ &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(&lt;span class=&#34;citeproc-not-found&#34; data-reference-id=&#34;gillespie_efficient_2016&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; (a concept mentioned in the slides not discussed in audio for lack of time) I provided some some example code that illustrated the kinds of techniques underlying the PCT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First download and visualise some transport data (from the Isle of Wight as, the smallest region in the PCT):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;u_pct = &amp;quot;https://github.com/npct/pct-data/raw/master/isle-of-wight/l.Rds&amp;quot;
if(!file.exists(&amp;quot;l.Rds&amp;quot;))
  download.file(u_pct, &amp;quot;l.Rds&amp;quot;)
l = readRDS(&amp;quot;l.Rds&amp;quot;)
library(sp)
plot(l)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2017-05-02-can-geographic-data-save-the-world_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have an idea of the commute patterns in the area, and the nature of ‘OD’ data (converted to geographical desire lines with the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr&#34;&gt;stplanr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; package), we can do some analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sel_walk = l$foot &amp;gt; 9
l_walk = l[sel_walk,]
plot(l)
plot(l_walk, add = T, col = &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;, lwd = 3)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2017-05-02-can-geographic-data-save-the-world_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(dplyr) # for next slide...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above code subsets all the lines that have 10 or more people walking to work in the 2011 census and plots the results (as you’d expect the shorter trips are more commonly walked). It works, but could be interpretted as a little clunky. Enter &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tidyverse/dplyr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dplyr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a package for data science &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(&lt;span class=&#34;citeproc-not-found&#34; data-reference-id=&#34;grolemund_r_2016&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;l_walk1 = l %&amp;gt;% filter(All &amp;gt; 10) # fails&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doh! That code nice ‘clean’ (well certainly consistent) code does not work because &lt;code&gt;Spatial&lt;/code&gt; objects are not compatible with the pipe operator &lt;code&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/code&gt; syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/edzer/sfr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package, which represents a step change in how R handles spatial data. First let’s convert that &lt;code&gt;l&lt;/code&gt; object into a ‘simple feature’ object:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(sf)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linking to GEOS 3.7.1, GDAL 2.4.0, PROJ 5.2.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## WARNING: different compile-time and runtime versions for GEOS found:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linked against: 3.7.1-CAPI-1.11.1 27a5e771 compiled against: 3.7.0-CAPI-1.11.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## It is probably a good idea to reinstall sf, and maybe rgeos and rgdal too&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;l_sf = st_as_sf(l)
class(l_sf)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] &amp;quot;sf&amp;quot;         &amp;quot;data.frame&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;plot(l_sf[6:15])&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: plotting the first 9 out of 10 attributes; use max.plot = 10 to
## plot all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2017-05-02-can-geographic-data-save-the-world_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than plotting multiples, one for each variable, objects of class &lt;code&gt;sf&lt;/code&gt; behave much like objects of class &lt;code&gt;Spatial&lt;/code&gt;, except they are also fully fledged data frames. This is what allows them to be subsetted with &lt;strong&gt;dplyr&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;code&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/code&gt; operator (reproducing the square bracket subsetting above):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;l_walk2 = l_sf %&amp;gt;% 
  filter(foot &amp;gt; 9)
plot(l_sf[6])
plot(l_walk2, add = T, lwd = 3)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in plot.sf(l_walk2, add = T, lwd = 3): ignoring all but the first
## attribute&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2017-05-02-can-geographic-data-save-the-world_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more advanced example involves the following: take all trips in the study area less than 1km and find those in which driving a car is more common than walking (areas that could have a major car dependency issue, the policy-relevant part):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;l_sf$distsf = as.numeric(st_length(l_sf))
l_drive_short = l_sf %&amp;gt;% 
  filter(distsf &amp;lt; 1000) %&amp;gt;% 
  filter(car_driver &amp;gt; foot)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tmap)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in fun(libname, pkgname): rgeos: versions of GEOS runtime 3.7.1-CAPI-1.11.1
## and GEOS at installation 3.7.0-CAPI-1.11.0differ&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tmap_mode(&amp;quot;view&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## tmap mode set to interactive viewing&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;qtm(l_drive_short)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:672px;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;leaflet html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;crs&#34;:{&#34;crsClass&#34;:&#34;L.CRS.EPSG3857&#34;,&#34;code&#34;:null,&#34;proj4def&#34;:null,&#34;projectedBounds&#34;:null,&#34;options&#34;:{}}},&#34;calls&#34;:[{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;createMapPane&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;tmap401&#34;,401]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;createMapPane&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;tmap402&#34;,402]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;Esri.WorldGrayCanvas&#34;,null,&#34;Esri.WorldGrayCanvas&#34;,{&#34;minZoom&#34;:0,&#34;maxZoom&#34;:18,&#34;tileSize&#34;:256,&#34;subdomains&#34;:&#34;abc&#34;,&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;tms&#34;:false,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;zoomOffset&#34;:0,&#34;zoomReverse&#34;:false,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;zIndex&#34;:1,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;pane&#34;:&#34;tilePane&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;OpenStreetMap&#34;,null,&#34;OpenStreetMap&#34;,{&#34;minZoom&#34;:0,&#34;maxZoom&#34;:18,&#34;tileSize&#34;:256,&#34;subdomains&#34;:&#34;abc&#34;,&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;tms&#34;:false,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;zoomOffset&#34;:0,&#34;zoomReverse&#34;:false,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;zIndex&#34;:1,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;pane&#34;:&#34;tilePane&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addProviderTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;Esri.WorldTopoMap&#34;,null,&#34;Esri.WorldTopoMap&#34;,{&#34;minZoom&#34;:0,&#34;maxZoom&#34;:18,&#34;tileSize&#34;:256,&#34;subdomains&#34;:&#34;abc&#34;,&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;tms&#34;:false,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;zoomOffset&#34;:0,&#34;zoomReverse&#34;:false,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;zIndex&#34;:1,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;pane&#34;:&#34;tilePane&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addPolylines&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[[[[{&#34;lng&#34;:[-1.29752372353896,-1.31007696611688],&#34;lat&#34;:[50.7571531462466,50.7534150222859]}]]],&#34;TRUE.&#34;,&#34;l_drive_short&#34;,{&#34;interactive&#34;:true,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;pane&#34;:&#34;tmap401&#34;,&#34;stroke&#34;:true,&#34;color&#34;:&#34;#000000&#34;,&#34;weight&#34;:1,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;fill&#34;:false,&#34;fillColor&#34;:&#34;#000000&#34;,&#34;fillOpacity&#34;:0.2,&#34;dashArray&#34;:&#34;none&#34;,&#34;smoothFactor&#34;:1,&#34;noClip&#34;:false},&#34;&lt;div style=\&#34;max-height:10em;overflow:auto;\&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;\n\t\t\t   &lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=\&#34;2\&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;TRUE&lt;\/b&gt;&lt;\/th&gt;&lt;\/thead&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;is_two_way&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TRUE&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dist&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.977&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;id&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;E02003581 E02003582&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;msoa1&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;E02003581&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;msoa2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;E02003582&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;all&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;759&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;light_rail&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;train&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;bus&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;24&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;taxi&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;motorbike&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;9&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;car_driver&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;344&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;car_passenger&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;44&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;bicycle&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;50&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;foot&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;282&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;other&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_slc&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;76.28&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sic&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;26.28&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_slw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;271.5&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_siw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-10.45&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sld&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;331.2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sid&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-12.75&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_slc&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;89.35&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sic&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;39.35&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_slw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;266.4&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_siw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-15.63&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sld&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;325.0&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sid&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-18.99&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_slc&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;221.2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sic&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;171.2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_slw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;213.9&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_siw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-68.12&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sld&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;260.9&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sid&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-83.12&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_slc&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;298.0&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sic&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;248.0&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_slw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;183.3&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_siw&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-98.66&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sld&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;223.6&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sid&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-120.4&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;base_sldeath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;base_slvalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2,613&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sldeath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.002&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_slvalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3,984&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sideath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sivalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1,371&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sldeath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.002&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_slvalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3,800&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sideath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sivalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1,187&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sldeath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.005&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_slvalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;9,212&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sideath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.004&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sivalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6,599&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sldeath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.002&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_slvalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-3,751&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sideath_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.003&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sivalue_webtag&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-6,364&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;base_sldeath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;base_slvalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2,105&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sldeath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.002&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_slvalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3,209&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sideath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sivalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1,104&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sldeath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.002&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_slvalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3,060&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sideath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sivalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;955&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sldeath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.004&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_slvalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;7,589&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sideath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-0.003&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sivalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5,484&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sldeath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.000&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_slvalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-185&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sideath_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sivalue_heat&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-2,290&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;base_slco2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-1,341&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_slco2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-2,047&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;govtarget_sico2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-706&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_slco2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-2,392&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;gendereq_sico2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-1,051&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_slco2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-5,945&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dutch_sico2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-4,604&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_slco2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-8,009&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;ebike_sico2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-6,668&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;geo_label1&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Isle of Wight 001&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;geo_label2&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Isle of Wight 002&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dist_fast&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.089&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;dist_quiet&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.085&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;time_fast&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;393&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;time_quiet&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;399&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;cirquity&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.115&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;distq_f&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.996&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;avslope&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3.122&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;avslope_q&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3.122&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;clc&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6.588&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=\&#34;color: #888888;\&#34;&gt;distsf&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;978.6&lt;\/td&gt;&lt;\/tr&gt;&lt;\/table&gt;&lt;\/div&gt;&#34;,{&#34;maxWidth&#34;:500,&#34;minWidth&#34;:100,&#34;autoPan&#34;:true,&#34;keepInView&#34;:false,&#34;closeButton&#34;:true,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;&#34;},&#34;TRUE&#34;,{&#34;interactive&#34;:false,&#34;permanent&#34;:false,&#34;direction&#34;:&#34;auto&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;offset&#34;:[0,0],&#34;textsize&#34;:&#34;10px&#34;,&#34;textOnly&#34;:false,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;sticky&#34;:true},null]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addLayersControl&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[[&#34;Esri.WorldGrayCanvas&#34;,&#34;OpenStreetMap&#34;,&#34;Esri.WorldTopoMap&#34;],&#34;l_drive_short&#34;,{&#34;collapsed&#34;:true,&#34;autoZIndex&#34;:true,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;topleft&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addScaleBar&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[{&#34;maxWidth&#34;:100,&#34;metric&#34;:true,&#34;imperial&#34;:false,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:true,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;bottomright&#34;}]}],&#34;limits&#34;:{&#34;lat&#34;:[50.7534150222859,50.7571531462466],&#34;lng&#34;:[-1.31007696611688,-1.29752372353896]},&#34;fitBounds&#34;:[50.7534150222859,-1.31007696611688,50.7571531462466,-1.29752372353896,[]]},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;discussion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was happy to find the talk was attended by a range of people, appropriate for a seminar about getting researchers down from the ivory towers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone from local government asked me if the above analysis to find short desire lines, along which more people drive than walk, could be applied in Liverpool (yes - the above code is a good starting point for working out how!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also asked how the PCT methodology could engage with established methods in transport planning. This is something that myself and others on the PCT team have discussed and it’s certainly given me a reason to revisit how best to do that (I don’t have a clear solution at the moment).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geographical research clearly can have policy impacts. Calling this ‘saving the world’ may seem like hyperbole, but it in my experience it can help communicate the message that publicly-funded academics usually work in the public interest, for the ‘greater good’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly the amount and direction of the policy impacts of your work will vary depending on a range of factors, many of which will be outside your sphere of influence. However, if you are a (geographical) ‘data scientist’, it seems that ensuring that the ‘science’ in your title is taken seriously can greatly improve your policy impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus reproducibility and free publication of data and results should not be seen as a bureaucratic burden. It can help you save the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-arribas-bel_accidental_2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arribas-Bel, Daniel. 2014. “Accidental, Open and Everywhere: Emerging Data Sources for the Understanding of Cities.” &lt;em&gt;Applied Geography&lt;/em&gt; 49: 45–53.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-lovelace_big_2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, Robin, Mark Birkin, Philip Cross, and Martin Clarke. 2016. “From Big Noise to Big Data: Toward the Verification of Large Data Sets for Understanding Regional Retail Flows.” &lt;em&gt;Geographical Analysis&lt;/em&gt; 48 (1): 59–81. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/gean.12081&#34;&gt;10.1111/gean.12081&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-lovelace_propensity_2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, Robin, Anna Goodman, Rachel Aldred, Nikolai Berkoff, Ali Abbas, and James Woodcock. 2017. “The Propensity to Cycle Tool: An Open Source Online System for Sustainable Transport Planning.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Transport and Land Use&lt;/em&gt; 10 (1). doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&#34;&gt;10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-singleton_gis_2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singleton, Alex. 2014. “A GIS Approach to Modelling Co2 Emissions Associated with the Pupil-School Commute.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Geographical Information Science&lt;/em&gt; 28 (2): 256–73. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1080/13658816.2013.832765&#34;&gt;10.1080/13658816.2013.832765&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The name of the discipline, broadly be defined geographic data analysis, modelling and visualisation, is an interesting topic in its own right. The preferred term to describe this body of work shifts over time, and depending on who you ask. Over the years it has been referred to as Geographic Information Systems (GIS, which sounds rather old school nowadays), the more academic-sounding Geographic Information Science (GISc), the concise term of Geocomputation and the more recently coined term of Geographic Data Science (GDS).&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Arribas-Bel (2014)&lt;/span&gt; for an alternative geographical take on Big Data.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I’m waxing lyrical about reproducibility and code I should practice what I preach. The source code of this article can be found at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rbind/robinlovelace/blob/master/content/post/2017-05-02-can-geographic-data-save-the-world.Rmd&#34;&gt;github.com/rbind/robinlovelace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seminar: invited talk at Geographic Data Science lab</title>
      <link>/presentations/gds-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/gds-seminar/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Talk at the Geographic Data Science (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/geographic-data-science/&#34;&gt;GDS&lt;/a&gt;) Lab in Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/can-gds-save-world.html#1&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to blogdown</title>
      <link>/2017/04/30/switching-to-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/30/switching-to-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I’ve finally got a new blog post, to test that my new set-up is working, using the wonderful new &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a test plot, to show how it allows R code to be embedded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;plot(1:9)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./post/2017-04-30-switching-to-blogdown_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have a quick-fire and fun way of getting new content onto the web I expect to be blogging lots more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this space!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CycleStreets.net in the Propensity to Cycle Tool</title>
      <link>/2016/12/21/cyclestreets.net-in-the-propensity-to-cycle-tool/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/12/21/cyclestreets.net-in-the-propensity-to-cycle-tool/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;After 2 years in the making, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jtlu.org/index.php/jtlu/article/view/862/824&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; describing the Propensity to Cycle Tool (PCT), and the thinking behind it, has finally been published (Lovelace et al. 2016). The PCT is an online tool for helping to decide where to prioritise cycling policies such as new cycle paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCT would not have been possible without CycleStreets.net, so as well as describing the PCT and it&amp;rsquo;s use of their routing services, this article serves as a big Thank You from PCT to CycleStreets.net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-propensity-to-cycle-tool&#34;&gt;What is the Propensity to Cycle Tool?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those new to the PCT, it&amp;rsquo;s an online tool for helping to decide where to prioritise cycling policies such as new cycle paths. It lives at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pct.bike&#34;&gt;http://www.pct.bike&lt;/a&gt; - check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The context of its development is explained in the accompanying video on that page. This article reports how the tool itself works and how it uses data from CycleStreets.net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCT is best understood by using it to explore current cycling levels, at regional, area, desire line, route and route network levels. We will take a look at how the PCT works at each of these levels, after a brief look at the scenario results at the regional level (the senarios are described in more detail in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jtlu.org/index.php/jtlu/article/view/862/824&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the 2011 Census scenario, the PCT represents levels of cycling to work based on the Census. This is a reasonable proxy for levels of utility cycling overall. We used origin-destination (OD) data from the Census as the basis of the PCT as this is best publicly available dataset on English travel patterns. The input data is described in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jtlu.org/index.php/jtlu/article/view/862&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; and can be freely downloaded from the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://wicid.ukdataservice.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;http://wicid.ukdataservice.ac.uk/&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-regional-picture-and-scenarios&#34;&gt;The regional picture and scenarios&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing the user sees on the front page is a map of England, broken into 44 regions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/figures/regions1.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used deliberately large regions because successful cycling plans should be strategic and joined up, covering both large areas and large spans of time. This discourages the stop-start investment plans that have typified funding for active travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By hovering over different regions, the user can see what the current level of cycling to work is. We can discover that West Yorkshire has a low current level of cycling to work, 1.3% in the 2011 census, and that Cambridgeshire has a relatively high (but low by Dutch standards) level of cycling of 9.7%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An exciting feature of the PCT is its ability to allow the user to imagine &amp;lsquo;cycling futures&amp;rsquo;. This can be seen on the front page map by clicking on the different scenarios (set to Census 2011 by default). We can see, for example, that under the Government Target to double cycling levels by 2025, West Yorkshire&amp;rsquo;s level would rise to 3.3% (more than a doubling) whereas Cambridgeshire would see cycling levels grow to 13.7% (a larger rise in absolute terms):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/figures/regions2.png?raw=true&#34; title=&#34;plot of chunk unnamed-chunk-2&#34; alt=&#34;plot of chunk unnamed-chunk-2&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/figures/regions3.png?raw=true&#34; title=&#34;plot of chunk unnamed-chunk-2&#34; alt=&#34;plot of chunk unnamed-chunk-2&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Go Dutch scenarios, these regions would see 23.1 and 13.5% of people cycling to work, respectively. This represents a huge leveling-out of cycling levels across the country, but still highlights the fact that some regions have higher cycling potentials than others, due to average trip distances and levels of hilliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cycling-levels-at-the-area-level&#34;&gt;Cycling levels at the area level&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To launch the PCT for a region, click on it.  Try clicking on West Yorkshire. You should be presented with the following image, which shows the area-based level of cycling to work from the 2011 Census. (When using the PCT, it is worth remembering that the visualisations work for every scenario.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/figures/west-yorkshire-front.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows that West Yorkshire has very low levels of cycling to work, hovering around 1% to 2% in most places. This suggests strongly that the region has low levels of utility cycling overall (despite the successes of the region&amp;rsquo;s sport cyclists). There is a cluster of zones with a higher level of cycling to the north of Leeds city centre (around Headingly) but even there the percentage of people cycling as their main mode of travel to work does not exceed 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cycling-potential-at-the-desire-line-level&#34;&gt;Cycling potential at the desire line level&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all useful information, especially when we look at how the cycling potential could shift in the future. However, it provides little information about where current and future cyclists actually go. This is where the desire line level can be useful. This can be selected by clicking on the Straight Lines option from the Cycling Flows dropdown menu. The results (zoomed in for Leeds) are shown in the figures below (see Figure 3 in the paper).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/flow-model/od-data-leeds.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/figures/leeds-desire-godutch.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the above figures show is that as the level of cycling increases in a city, the spatial distribution of cycling can be expected to change. Under current conditions (be they related to socio-demographics or infrastructure or other factors), cycling in Leeds is dominated by the travel corridor to the north of the city centre. Yet there are clearly many short trips taking place from the south into the centre, as illustrated by the high cycling potential south of the city under the Go Dutch scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;allocating-cycling-potential-to-the-route-network&#34;&gt;Allocating cycling potential to the route network&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where CycleStreets.net comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know how many people go from A to B by cycling from Census data. But we have very little idea of how they are likely to travel. This is where the routing algorithm of CycleStreets.net comes in handy. We used their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cyclestreets.net/api/apply/&#34;&gt;routing API&lt;/a&gt; to estimate the &amp;lsquo;fastest&amp;rsquo; route for all short (well, up to 20 km in Euclidean distance) desire lines in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only does CycleStreets.net allow us to find all the fastest routes, a good indication of where new infrastructure should be built as people (especially women and elderly) have a strong preference for cycling along the most direct routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of all this routing work is illustrated in the future below, which shows the fastest and quietest routes associated with the top cycled routes in Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/flow-model/od-data-fast-quiet.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the big fat line up to the north-west is Otley Road, well-known to have very high level of cycling. This also shows up in Strava data as having high current levels of cycling:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/blob/master/figures/pct-vs-strava-for-leeds.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not formal validation but it is a good sign that the PCT and other data sources line-up for the current level of cycling. The big question is whether the PCT&amp;rsquo;s estimates of cycling levels under various cycling futures, including Go Dutch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is not the place to answer such a question. Only the passage of time, and commitment from people (perhaps informed by models such as the PCT) to sustainable travel will help answer that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more to say about the use of CycleStreets.net in the PCT but it gets rather technical very quickly.
Suffice to say at this stage that it involved writing lots of code in R, a language for statistical programming, and that this has now resulted in the publication of &lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr&#34;&gt;an R package for sustainable transport&lt;/a&gt;.
(For more on how to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;install R&lt;/a&gt; and (for bells and whistles) RStudio, which this blog post was written in, please see the relevant sections of the book &lt;a href=&#34;https://csgillespie.github.io/efficientR/set-up.html#installing-r&#34;&gt;Efficent R Programming&lt;/a&gt; (Gillespie and Lovelace, 2016).)
With R installed, &lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt; can be installed with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;stplanr&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this package installed, you can start using the CycleStreets.net routing algorithm with the following function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(stplanr)
route = route_cyclestreet(from = &amp;quot;Leeds&amp;quot;, to = &amp;quot;Cambridge&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which results in spatial data, which can be visualised as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(leaflet)
leaflet() %&amp;gt;% addTiles() %&amp;gt;% addPolylines(data = route)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://robinlovelace.net/leeds-cam-map.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more I could say about the technical side of things but at the request of the editors I will leave it there for now. For more info please see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr/blob/master/vignettes/stplanr-paper.Rmd&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt; vignette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to follow this overview article up with a more technical blog post in the New Year. Watch this space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Goodman, A., Aldred, R., Berkoff, N., Abbas, A., &amp;amp; Woodcock, J. (2016). The Propensity to Cycle Tool: An open source online system for sustainable transport planning. Journal Of Transport And Land Use, 0. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geostat2016 Albacete: a write-up</title>
      <link>/2016/09/28/geostat2016-albacete-a-write-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/09/28/geostat2016-albacete-a-write-up/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last week I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/2016&#34;&gt;GEOSTAT 2016&lt;/a&gt;. Given the amount of fun had at &lt;a href=&#34;http://robinlovelace.net/r/2015/08/31/geostat-writeup.html&#34;&gt;GEOSTAT 2015&lt;/a&gt;, expectations were high. The local organisers did not disappoint, with a week of lectures, workshops, spatial data competitions and of course lots of Geostatistics. It would be unwise to try to systematically document such a diverse range of activities, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/node&#34;&gt;GEOSTAT website&lt;/a&gt; provides much further info. Instead this &amp;lsquo;miniwriteup&amp;rsquo; is designed to summarise some of my memories from the event, and encourage you to get involved for GEOSTAT 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put things in context, the first session was a brief overview of the history of GEOSTAT. This is the 12&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; GEOSTAT summer school. In some ways GEOSTAT can be seen as a physical manifestation of the lively &lt;a href=&#34;https://stat.ethz.ch/mailman/listinfo/r-sig-geo&#34;&gt;R-SIG-GEO email list&lt;/a&gt;. That may not sound very exciting. But there is a strong community spirit at the event and, unlike other academic conferences, the focus is on practical learning rather than transmitting research findings or theories. And the event was so much more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 5 action packed days covering many topics within the broad field of Geostatistics. What follows is an overview of each that I went to (there were 2 streams), with links to the source material. It is hoped that this will be of use to people who were not present in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1&#34;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an introduction to the course and spatial data by Tom Hengl, Roger Bivand delivered a technical and applied webinar on &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/system/files/geostat_talk16.pdf&#34;&gt;bridges between R and other GIS software&lt;/a&gt;. With a focus on GRASS, we learned how R could be used as a &amp;lsquo;front end&amp;rsquo; to other programs. An example using the famous &amp;lsquo;Cholera pump&amp;rsquo; data mapped by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Snow&#34;&gt;John Snow&lt;/a&gt; was used to demonstrate the potential benefits of &amp;lsquo;bridging&amp;rsquo; to other software. The data can be downloaded and partially plotted in R as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;u = &amp;quot;http://geostat-course.org/system/files/data_0.zip&amp;quot;
download.file(u, &amp;quot;data_0.zip&amp;quot;)
unzip(&amp;quot;data_0.zip&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;old = setwd(&amp;quot;~/repos/geostat2016-rl/&amp;quot;)
library(raster)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Loading required package: sp
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;bbo = shapefile(&amp;quot;data/bbo.shp&amp;quot;)
buildings = shapefile(&amp;quot;data/buildings.shp&amp;quot;)
deaths = shapefile(&amp;quot;data/deaths.shp&amp;quot;)
b_pump = shapefile(&amp;quot;data/b_pump.shp&amp;quot;)
nb_pump = shapefile(&amp;quot;data/nb_pump.shp&amp;quot;)
plot(buildings)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/raw/master/figures/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;setwd(old)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon Robert Hijmans gave a high level overview of software for spatial data analysis, with a discussion of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.diva-gis.org/&#34;&gt;Diva GIS&lt;/a&gt; software he developed and why he now uses R for most of his geospatial analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk touched on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/gdistance/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gdistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package, and many others. Robert showcased the power of R for understanding major civilisational problems such as the impacts of climate change on agriculture. His animated global maps of agricultural productivity and precipitation showed how R can scale to tackle large datasets, up to the global level involving spatial and temporal data simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few political asides. Robert mentioned how agrotech giant Monsanto paid almost &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastcoexist.com/3019387/why-monsanto-just-spent-1-billion-to-buy-a-climate-data-company&#34;&gt;$1 billion&lt;/a&gt; for a weather prediction company. He detoured deftly through a discussion of &amp;lsquo;big data&amp;rsquo;, making the observation that often ensembles of models can provide better predictions than any single model working on its own, with political analogies about the importance of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More examples included health and estimates of dietary deficiencies at high levels of geographic resolution. A paper showing fish and fruit consumption across Rwanda illustrated how map making in R, used intelligently, can save lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was revealing to learn how Robert got into R. While he was working at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://irri.org/&#34;&gt;International Rice Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;ldquo;It forces you to write scripts.&amp;rdquo; This is good for ensuring reproducibility, a critical component of scientific research. It encourages you to focus on and understand the data primarily, rather than visualising it. On the other hand, R is not always the fastest way to do things, although &amp;ldquo;people often worry too much about this&amp;rdquo;. Your time is more important than your computers, so setting an analysis running is fine. Plus there are ways to make things run faster, as mentioned in a book that I&amp;rsquo;m working on, &lt;a href=&#34;https://csgillespie.github.io/efficientR/&#34;&gt;Efficient R Programming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R is great if you use it every data, but if you only use it less than once a week it becomes difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you just want a one-off spatial analysis data program, Robert recommended QGIS. After a brief overview of spatial data in R, Robert moved on to talk about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/raster/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;raster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package, which he developed. This package was developed to overcome some of the limitations with &lt;strong&gt;sp&lt;/strong&gt;, the foundational package for spatial data in R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- This led on to discussion of C++ code, which Robert is increasingly developing in to extend **raster**. Here is a brief benchmark to show how much faster C++ code can be: --&gt;

&lt;!-- ```{r} --&gt;

&lt;!-- sumR = function(x){ --&gt;

&lt;!--   b = NULL --&gt;

&lt;!--   for(i in 1:length(x)){ --&gt;

&lt;!--     b = b + a[i] --&gt;

&lt;!--   } --&gt;

&lt;!-- } --&gt;

&lt;!-- ``` --&gt;

&lt;!-- ```{r, engine=&#39;cpp&#39;, eval=FALSE} --&gt;

&lt;!-- library(Rcpp) --&gt;

&lt;!-- cppFunction(code =  --&gt;

&lt;!--               &#34;// [[Rcpp::export]] --&gt;

&lt;!-- double cumulater(std::vector&lt;doubl&gt;d) { --&gt;

&lt;!--   int n = x.size(); --&gt;

&lt;!--   double result = 0; --&gt;

&lt;!--   for (int i=0;i &lt; n; i++) { --&gt;

&lt;!--     result = result + d[i]; --&gt;

&lt;!--   } --&gt;

&lt;!--   double r = cumulater(v) --&gt;

&lt;!-- }return r;&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- ``` --&gt;

&lt;!-- According to Robert, once you can write R functions, &#34;writing C++ functions is relatively easy&#34;. While I&#39;m not quite convinced, based on the number of characters needed to write a simple sum code, he certainly convinced me of the merits of developing new spatial functions in this low level language, because of its speed and the fact that it&#39;s the main development language of GDAL.  --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final resource that Robert promoted was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rspatial.org/&#34;&gt;RSpatial.org&lt;/a&gt;, a free online resource for teaching R as a command line GIS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edzer Pebesmer delivered the final session of the first day, on &lt;strong&gt;Free and Open Source Software (FOSS) for Geoinformatics and Geosciences&lt;/strong&gt;. After the highly technical final C++ examples from the previous talk, I was expecting a high level overview of the landscape. Instead Edzer went straight in to talk about source code, the raw material that defines all software. The fundamental feature of open source software is that its source code is free, and will remain free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- An example of this is Apple, the most profitable computer company on Earth, used parts of the BSD kernel in its proprietary operating system. --&gt;

&lt;!-- Another feature of open source software is that it must have a license. It has a legal meaning, the details of which vary from licence to license. By deciding a license, you can choose whether you use a more *restrictive* license (which prevents people from using the software in software that is solved) or a more *permisive* license. R&#39;s &#39;backend&#39; is licensed --&gt;

&lt;!-- GPL is used for R&#39;s. ESRI is now using R as a back-end in commercial software. Its lawers have explored the legal implications of this and concluded that it is not breaking the law by doing so. --&gt;

&lt;!-- GitHub is an online system for developing open source software. It is free to use, but some of the best things in GitHub are not open source. Edzer says that the advantages of using their service, in terms of community engagement and ease of use and accessibility, currently outweigh any potential future disbenefits of GitHub not being completely open source.  --&gt;

&lt;!-- Another example is open source software for geosciences. Researchers may want to make their software open for anyone to use, while remaining protected from exploitation from large companies like oil com --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-2&#34;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day of the course was divided in two: stream A focussed on environmental modelling and stream B compositional data. I attended the environmental modelling course taught by Robert Hijmans. The course was based on his teaching material at &lt;a href=&#34;http://rspatial.org/spatial/index.html&#34;&gt;rspatial.org&lt;/a&gt; and can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://gfc.ucdavis.edu/events/albacete/day2.html&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off by looking at the fundamental data structures underlying spatial data in R. Why? It&amp;rsquo;s useful to be able to create simple example datasets from scratch, to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(sp)
x &amp;lt;- c(4,7,3,8)
y &amp;lt;- c(9,6,12,11)
xy &amp;lt;- data.frame(x, y)
SpatialPoints(xy)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## class       : SpatialPoints 
## features    : 4 
## extent      : 3, 8, 6, 12  (xmin, xmax, ymin, ymax)
## coord. ref. : NA
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;d = data.frame(v1 = 1:4, v2 = LETTERS[1:4])
spd = SpatialPointsDataFrame(coords = xy, data = d)
plot(spd)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/raw/master/figures/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic functions of the &lt;strong&gt;raster&lt;/strong&gt; package are similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(raster)
r = raster(nc = 10, nr = 10)
values(r) = 1:ncell(r)
plot(r)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/raw/master/figures/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;as.matrix(r)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##       [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4] [,5] [,6] [,7] [,8] [,9] [,10]
##  [1,]    1    2    3    4    5    6    7    8    9    10
##  [2,]   11   12   13   14   15   16   17   18   19    20
##  [3,]   21   22   23   24   25   26   27   28   29    30
##  [4,]   31   32   33   34   35   36   37   38   39    40
##  [5,]   41   42   43   44   45   46   47   48   49    50
##  [6,]   51   52   53   54   55   56   57   58   59    60
##  [7,]   61   62   63   64   65   66   67   68   69    70
##  [8,]   71   72   73   74   75   76   77   78   79    80
##  [9,]   81   82   83   84   85   86   87   88   89    90
## [10,]   91   92   93   94   95   96   97   98   99   100
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;q = sqrt(r)
plot(q)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/raw/master/figures/unnamed-chunk-7-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;x = q + r
s = stack(r, q, x)
ss = s * r # r is recycled so each layer is multiplied by r
1:3 * 2 # here 2 is recycled
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 2 4 6
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raster also provides simple yet powerful functions for manipulating and analysing raster data, including &lt;code&gt;crop()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;merge()&lt;/code&gt; for manipulation and &lt;code&gt;predict()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;focal()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;distance()&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;predict()&lt;/code&gt; is particularly interesting as it allows raster values to be estimated using any of R&amp;rsquo;s powerful statistical methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(dismo)
g = gmap(&amp;quot;Albacete, Spain&amp;quot;, scale = T, lonlat = T)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Loading required namespace: XML
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;plot(g, interpolate = T)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/raw/master/figures/unnamed-chunk-9-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/npct/pct/raw/master/figures/unnamed-chunk-9-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;dismo::geocode(&amp;quot;Universidad Castilla la Mancha&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##                    originalPlace
## 1 Universidad Castilla la Mancha
##                                          interpretedPlace longitude
## 1 Paseo Universidad, 13005 Ciudad Real, Cdad. Real, Spain -3.921711
##   latitude      xmin      xmax     ymin     ymax uncertainty
## 1 38.99035 -3.922007 -3.919309 38.98919 38.99189         131
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;!-- Supervised learning is the process of allowing a computer to estimate predictor variables based on explanatory variables. --&gt;

&lt;!-- There are 2 main things to consider when model fitting: the functional form to use and the explanatory variables X. --&gt;

&lt;!-- We worked through a practical on spatial interpolation from [rspatial.org](http://rspatial.org/analysis/rst/4-interpolation.html): --&gt;

&lt;!-- ```{r} --&gt;

&lt;!-- dir.create(&#34;data&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- download.file(&#34;http://rspatial.org/analysis/data/precipitation.csv&#34;, &#34;data/precipitation.csv&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- d = read.csv(&#34;data/precipitation.csv&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- d$prec &lt;- rowSums(d[, c(6:17)]) --&gt;

&lt;!-- plot(sort(d$prec), ylab=&#39;Annual precipitation (mm)&#39;, las=1, xlab=&#39;Stations&#39;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- library(sp) --&gt;

&lt;!-- dsp &lt;- SpatialPoints(d[,4:3], proj4string=CRS(&#34;+proj=longlat +datum=NAD83&#34;)) --&gt;

&lt;!-- dsp &lt;- SpatialPointsDataFrame(dsp, d) --&gt;

&lt;!-- download.file(&#34;http://rspatial.org/analysis/data/counties.rds&#34;, &#34;data/counties.rds&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- CA &lt;- readRDS(&#34;data/counties.rds&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- # define groups for mapping --&gt;

&lt;!-- cuts &lt;- c(0,200,300,500,1000,3000) --&gt;

&lt;!-- # set up a palette of interpolated colors --&gt;

&lt;!-- blues &lt;- colorRampPalette(c(&#39;yellow&#39;, &#39;orange&#39;, &#39;blue&#39;, &#39;dark blue&#39;)) --&gt;

&lt;!-- pols &lt;- list(&#34;sp.polygons&#34;, CA, fill = &#34;lightgray&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- spplot(dsp, &#39;prec&#39;, cuts=cuts, col.regions=blues(5), sp.layout=pols, pch=20, cex=2) --&gt;

&lt;!-- TA &lt;- CRS(&#34;+proj=aea +lat_1=34 +lat_2=40.5 +lat_0=0 +lon_0=-120 +x_0=0 +y_0=-4000000 +datum=NAD83 +units=m +ellps=GRS80 +towgs84=0,0,0&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- library(rgdal) --&gt;

&lt;!-- dta &lt;- spTransform(dsp, TA) --&gt;

&lt;!-- cata &lt;- spTransform(CA, TA) --&gt;

&lt;!-- ``` --&gt;

&lt;!-- Now the modelling work can begin.  --&gt;

&lt;!-- ```{r} --&gt;

&lt;!-- # First create a function to calculate the error: --&gt;

&lt;!-- RMSE &lt;- function(observed, predicted) { --&gt;

&lt;!--   sqrt(mean((predicted - observed)^2, na.rm=TRUE)) --&gt;

&lt;!-- } --&gt;

&lt;!-- null &lt;- RMSE(mean(dsp$prec), dsp$prec) --&gt;

&lt;!-- null --&gt;

&lt;!-- library(dismo) --&gt;

&lt;!-- v &lt;- voronoi(dta) --&gt;

&lt;!-- ## Loading required namespace: deldir --&gt;

&lt;!-- plot(dsp) --&gt;

&lt;!-- plot(v) --&gt;

&lt;!-- points(dta, col = &#34;red&#34;) --&gt;

&lt;!-- ca = aggregate(cata) --&gt;

&lt;!-- plot(ca) --&gt;

&lt;!-- vca = intersect(v, ca) --&gt;

&lt;!-- plot(vca) --&gt;

&lt;!-- vca2 = rgeos::gIntersection(v, ca, byid = T) --&gt;

&lt;!-- names(vca2) --&gt;

&lt;!-- plot(vca2) # not the same! --&gt;

&lt;!-- plot(vca) --&gt;

&lt;!-- names(vca) --&gt;

&lt;!-- ``` --&gt;

&lt;!-- Testing a first model --&gt;

&lt;!-- ```{r} --&gt;

&lt;!-- kf = kfold(dta@data) --&gt;

&lt;!-- rmse = NULL --&gt;

&lt;!-- for(k in 1:length(unique(kf))){ --&gt;

&lt;!--   test = dta[kf == k,] --&gt;

&lt;!--   train = dta[kf != k,] --&gt;

&lt;!--   v = voronoi(train) --&gt;

&lt;!--   p = extract(v, test) --&gt;

&lt;!--   rmse[k] = RMSE(observed = test$prec, predicted = p$prec) --&gt;

&lt;!-- } --&gt;

&lt;!-- rmse --&gt;

&lt;!-- ``` --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-3&#34;&gt;Day 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third day started with a live R demo by Edzer Pebesmer on &lt;a href=&#34;https://edzer.github.io/UseR2016/&#34;&gt;space-time data&lt;/a&gt;. Refreshingly for a conference primarily on spatial data, it started with an in-depth discussion of time. While base R natively supports temporal units (knowing the difference between days and seconds, for example) it does not know the difference between metres and miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This led to the creation of the &lt;strong&gt;units&lt;/strong&gt; library, an taster of which is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;units&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(units)
m = with(ud_units,  m)
s = with(ud_units,  s)
km = with(ud_units, km)
h = with(ud_units,  h)
x = 1:3 * m/s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the day was spent analysing a range of spatio-temporal datasets using &lt;strong&gt;spacetime&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;trajectories&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;rgl&lt;/strong&gt; for interactive 3d spacetime plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the parallel session there were sessions on &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/node/1328&#34;&gt;CARTO&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/node/1329&#34;&gt;R gvSIG bridge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-4&#34;&gt;Day 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 4 was a highlight for me as I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to learn how to use the &lt;strong&gt;INLA&lt;/strong&gt; package for ages. It was explained lucidly by Marta Blangiardo and Michela Cameletti, who have written an excellent book on the subject, which has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/a/r-inla.org/stbook/&#34;&gt;website that I recommend checking out&lt;/a&gt;. Their materials can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/node/1330&#34;&gt;http://geostat-course.org/node/1330&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel to this there was a session on &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/node/1326&#34;&gt;Spatial and Spatiotemporal point process analysis in R&lt;/a&gt; data in R by Virgilio Gomez Rubio and one on automated &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/node/1323&#34;&gt;spatial prediction and visualisation&lt;/a&gt; by Tom Hengl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-5&#34;&gt;Day 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all that intense geospatial analysis and programming activity, and a night out in Albacete for some participants, we were relieved to learn that this final day of learning was more relaxed. Furthermore, by tradition, it was largely participant-led. I gave a talk on &lt;a href=&#34;https://csgillespie.github.io/efficientR/&#34;&gt;Efficient R Programming&lt;/a&gt;, a book I&amp;rsquo;ve written in collaboration with Colin Gillespie; Teresa Rojos gave a fascinating talk about her research into the spatial distribution of cancer rates in Peru; and S.J. Norder gave us the low-down on the Biogeography of islands with R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting sessions was the revelation of the results of the spatial prediction game. Interestingly, a team using a relatively simple approach with &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/randomForestSRC/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;randomForestSRC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ehrlinger/ggRandomForests&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ggRandomForests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for visualisation) one against others who had spent hours training complex multi-level models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall it was an amazing event and inspiring to spend time with so many researchers using open geospatial software for tackling &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/UqMyCnXOsG&#34;&gt;pressing real world issues&lt;/a&gt;. Furthermore, it was great fun. I strongly recommend people dipping their toes in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/views/Spatial.html&#34;&gt;sea of spatial capabilities&lt;/a&gt; provided by R check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://geostat-course.org/node&#34;&gt;GEOSTAT website&lt;/a&gt;, not least for the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://archive.org/search.php?query=GEOSTAT&#34;&gt;video resources to be found there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to hearing plans for future GEOSTATs and recommend the event, and associated materials, to researchers interested in using free geospatial software for the greater good.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keynote: Cycling and transport policy</title>
      <link>/presentations/hackney-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/hackney-keynote/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Invited keynote lecture titled &lt;em&gt;Cycling and transport policy: embedding active travel in every stage of the planning process&lt;/em&gt;, at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hackney.gov.uk/cycling-conference&#34;&gt;Hackney Cycling Conference&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/RobinLovelace/188175&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R vs QGIS for sustainable transport planning</title>
      <link>/2015/01/20/r-vs-qgis-for-sustainable-transport-planning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/20/r-vs-qgis-for-sustainable-transport-planning/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The 23rd iteration of the GIS Research UK conference
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/stplanr&#34;&gt;#GISRUK&lt;/a&gt;)
conference was the largest ever. 250 researchers,
industry representatives and academics attended from the
vibrant geospatial research communities in the
UK, Europe and beyond. GISRUK has become a centrepoint for discussion
of new methods, software and applications in the field. I
was on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://leeds.gisruk.org/contact.html&#34;&gt;organising committee&lt;/a&gt;,
reviewed some excellent papers for the event
(a full list of these is
&lt;a href=&#34;http://leeds.gisruk.org/programme.html&#34;&gt;available for download here&lt;/a&gt;) and
attended some truly ground-breaking talks.
This experience has shown that the geospatial community
in the UK is strong,
especially with regards to growth in open access
data and open source software in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/17025120518&#34; title=&#34;img_2814 by Robin Lovelace, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5450/17025120518_ebfba47bff_s.jpg&#34; width=&#34;75&#34; height=&#34;75&#34; alt=&#34;img_2814&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is about one part of GISRUK and insights gleaned from it
about R, QGIS and other tools for sustainable transport planning.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/GIS4TA&#34;&gt;GIS for Transport Applications&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/gis4ta?src=hash&#34;&gt;#GIS4TA for short&lt;/a&gt;) was a practical day-long workshop
that preceded the main event.
I organised the workshop and (with help from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geog.leeds.ac.uk/people/e.odiari&#34;&gt;Eusebio Odiari&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tgrg.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;The Transport Geography Research Group&lt;/a&gt;
and the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rgs.org/HomePage.htm&#34;&gt;Royal Geographical Society&lt;/a&gt;)
it seems to have been a great success. More than 30
people attended, including a decent portion
from transport consultancies such as
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itpworld.net/index.html&#34;&gt;Integrated Transport Planning Ltd&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trpconsult.com/&#34;&gt;TRP Consulting&lt;/a&gt; and the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.era.europa.eu/Pages/Home.aspx&#34;&gt;European Railway Association (ERA)&lt;/a&gt;.
Specifically, it is about the use of R
and QGIS tools for transport planning and the potential for their
adoption in academic, public and private-sector transport planning.
The focus of the workshop was deliberately on open source software
and sustainable transport because these are growth
areas in the field that are essential for
democratic
and healthy
transport systems compatible with the
science of climate change (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opentraffic.net/en/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Tamminga, 2012&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).
A recent report, for example, suggests we need to almost completely
transition away from fossil fuels by 2050
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature14016&#34;&gt;McGlade et al., 2015&lt;/a&gt;).
New datasets and methods for analysing and modelling them can
help get us there in the recalcitrant transport sector
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2014.07.010&#34;&gt;Gossling, 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;r-for-transport-applications&#34;&gt;R for transport applications&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop kicked-off with a short
talk on &amp;lsquo;R and QGIS for transport applications&amp;rsquo;,
which laid out some of the motivations for running the
workshop outlined above. Other than a few
&amp;lsquo;early adopters&amp;rsquo;, the transport modelling community
is generally conservative, based largely on mature
proprietary products such as
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.saturnsoftware.co.uk/7.html&#34;&gt;SATURN&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://vision-traffic.ptvgroup.com/en-us/products/ptv-vissim/&#34;&gt;Vissim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slides from this talk are available here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;91fce9cf5c36405b8969c6b6954c4fe6&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.41436464088398&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorial: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/GIS4TA/releases/download/0.1/intro-r-qgis-4ta.pdf&#34;&gt;Introduction to R and QGIS for transport applications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;routing-with-r&#34;&gt;Routing with R&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second talk was by Nick Bearman, who provided an overview of
routing in R, as well as an excellent
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nickbearman/transport-workshop/blob/master/transport-workshop.pdf&#34;&gt;practical tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practical demonstrated 2 ways of routing in R:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;strong&gt;ggmap&lt;/strong&gt;. The following code was used to navigate to the event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from &amp;lt;- &#39;Leeds station, New Station Street, Leeds LS1 5DL, United Kingdom&#39;
to &amp;lt;- &#39;LS2 9JT&#39;
route_df &amp;lt;- route(from, to, structure = &#39;route&#39;, mode = &#39;walking&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;qmap(&#39;Merrion Centre&#39;, zoom = 15) +
geom_path(
aes(x = lon, y = lat),  colour = &#39;red&#39;, size = 1.5,
data = route_df, lineend = &#39;round&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/robinlovelace.github.io/raw/master/_posts/writeup_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/stplanr&#34;&gt;package I created, &lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
to get routes optimised for cyclists (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nickbearman/transport-workshop/blob/master/transport-workshop.Rmd&#34;&gt;transport-workshop.Rmd&lt;/a&gt; for a working version):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rquiet &amp;lt;- gLines2CyclePath(l = rlines, plan = &amp;quot;quietest&amp;quot;)
plot(rquiet[1,]) # route from Leeds station to Leeds University (North - South)
plot(rquiet[2,]) # route from Leeds to Manchester!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/robinlovelace.github.io/raw/master/_posts/writeup_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorial: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nickbearman/transport-workshop/blob/master/transport-workshop.pdf&#34;&gt;Route analysis using R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;large-gps-datasets-with-postgis&#34;&gt;Large gps datasets with PostGIS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most technical session involved using R to query huge datasets storing
GPS data containing 100,000+ rows. Amazingly, Richard and Adrian Ellison
set up a remotely accessible database instance &lt;strong&gt;from their laptop&lt;/strong&gt; which
participants queried via
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/RPostgreSQL/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RPostgreSQL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Their session information can be seen here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/richardellison/GIS4TA_GPS&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;github.com/richardellison/GIS4TA_GPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-hackathon&#34;&gt;A hackathon&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally there was a miniature hackathon organised by Godwin Yeboah.
Participants made progress in better understanding the travel
patterns of cyclists using real data. The hackathon notes can be found here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spatialscientist/GIS4TA2015&#34;&gt;github.com/spatialscientist/GIS4TA2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GIS is a field of knowledge that has a huge amount to offer transport
planners and researchers, especially regarding new and open source
software tools that can effectively generate, process and analyse
transport-related data. R is well-suited to fill this research gap and
has a wide range of tools to help. Packages such as &lt;strong&gt;ggmap&lt;/strong&gt;
(Kahle and Wickham 2013),
&lt;strong&gt;RPostgreSQL&lt;/strong&gt;
and the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/stplanr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stplanr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
have great potential to help plan the transport systems of the future.
QGIS is also increasingly attractive for transport applications, with
it inbuilt support for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://planet.qgis.org/planet/tag/pgrouting/&#34;&gt;PGRouting&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://plugins.qgis.org/plugins/FlowMapper/&#34;&gt;flow analysis&lt;/a&gt;
and a friendly user interface that many will be used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos taken during the hackathon are testament to its role as a forum
for not only learning but also debate about the future of GIS in transport.
These can be seen here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/sets/72157652012715766&#34;&gt;flickr.com/photos/97888609@N02/sets/72157652012715766&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hearing feedback from users new to R using it to solve transport problems
provided an insight into how it compares to traditional tools. The removal
of &amp;lsquo;glass ceilings&amp;rsquo; imposed by restrictive licenses or the need to buy
&amp;lsquo;add-on&amp;rsquo; features was one comment, but that applies equally to QGIS and
other &lt;a href=&#34;http://foss4g.org/&#34;&gt;FOSS4G&lt;/a&gt;
offerings. The steep learning curve of R seems to still
be an issue compared with QGIS, although this is becoming less of an issue
with the evolution of RStudio as an GUI for R. In conclusion, both R and
QGIS are coming of age as tools in the transport planner&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;war cabinet&amp;rsquo;.
The latest evidence unequivocally shows the impact of transport decisions
on obesity, environmental degradation and quality of life. So it is time,
surely, to harness this new open source software to &amp;lsquo;save the world&amp;rsquo;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Consumer Data Research Centre and the Royal Geographical
society for subsidising the event. Thanks to all the participants and
especially the demonstrators Godwin, Nick, Adrian and Richard for making it
happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gössling, Stefan, and Scott Cohen. 2014. “Why sustainable transport policies will fail: EU climate policy in the light of transport taboos.” Journal of Transport Geography 39 (July). Elsevier Ltd: 197–207. doi:10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2014.07.010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kahle, D, and Hadley Wickham. 2013. “ggmap: Spatial Visualization with ggplot2.” The R Journal 5: 144–61. &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.375.8693&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34;&gt;citeseerx.ist.psu.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGlade, Christophe, and Paul Ekins. 2015. “The geographical distribution of fossil fuels unused when limiting global warming to 2 °C.” Nature 517 (7533). Nature Publishing Group: 187–90. doi:10.1038/nature14016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tamminga, Guus, Marc Miska, Edgar Santos, Hans van Lint, Arturo Nakasone, Helmut Prendinger, and Serge Hoogendoorn. 2012. “Design of Open Source Framework for Traffic and Travel Simulation.” Transportation Research Record: Journal of the Transportation Research Board 2291 (-1): 44–52. doi:10.&lt;sup&gt;3141&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2291&lt;/sub&gt;-06.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future Is Not What It Used To Be - Book review</title>
      <link>/2014/01/28/the-future-is-not-what-it-used-to-be-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/28/the-future-is-not-what-it-used-to-be-book-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is a review I was invited to write for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.erica.demon.co.uk/EV.html&#34;&gt;Environmental Values&lt;/a&gt;,
a journal for academics to publish their musings on the state of the
environment and what is to be done about it. I found the book good, but was
perhaps overly gushing in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.erica.demon.co.uk/EV/reviews/76_Friedrichs.pdf&#34;&gt;my review&lt;/a&gt;
on their website in hindsight. Why? Well since my review there have been
another couple of assessments from respected sources that are mixed to
say the least. Sarah Lester, writing for the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/lsereviewofbooks/2013/12/20/book-review-the-future-is-not-what-it-used-to-be/&#34;&gt;LSE&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;
points out that when things get bad,
the logical reaction is not to ponder things and have an existential crisis
but to ACT. The second review, in the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/books/the-future-is-not-what-it-used-to-be-climate-change-and-energy-scarcity-by-jrg-friedrichs/2007555.article&#34;&gt;Times Higher Education&lt;/a&gt;
acknowledges the reasoning behind Friedrichs&amp;rsquo; pessimism but statest that
it&amp;rsquo;s simply not too late to give up. I take both points but would only add
that the book also has something important to offer optimists: a sober
reality check about the severity of the situation we&amp;rsquo;re in and a motivation
to make our actions more intelligently. All in all, I still stand by
everything I said in the original review, found below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-take-on-it&#34;&gt;My take on it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope of the book is not only to explore the intertwined problems of climate change and peak oil, but also to assess the chances of an effective response. It becomes clear in the first few pages that The Future is a unique contribution. Many authors have written about the scale of the problem and bemoaned the lack of action; fewer have adequately explained inaction, or honestly appraised the likely impacts of collective failure. In a refreshingly stark and honest beginning to the book, Friedrichs sets out his aim, to “explain our inability to adequately grasp and confront our predicament” (p. viii). This review assesses the work on two levels: firstly it is assessed in its own terms - how well does it meet its aim? Secondly, I offer a more general assessment of the book&amp;rsquo;s worth, from the perspective of an optimistic environmental geographer eager for a &amp;lsquo;post-carbon&amp;rsquo; future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few would question the importance of the former criterion: tackling the root causes of the &amp;lsquo;Long Emergency&amp;rsquo; of global industrial society is a challenge to which we must rise to create a liveable future (Kunstler 2006). The long-running debate will undoubtedly benefit from new perspectives and fresh assessments of the evidence. A more challenging question to ask of any book facing up to such grim realities yet targeted squarely at the &amp;lsquo;lay&amp;rsquo; public is whether it can actually be fun and accessible, whilst maintaining its rigour and commitment to the evidence. Impatient readers will be pleased to learn that the blunt answer is a decisive &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo;. The more subtle answer, of course, depends largely on the reader. It is therefore worth taking a quick detour to consider the type of person who might be interested such an ominous title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small but committed group of people find books about the &amp;lsquo;big picture&amp;rsquo; to be addictive. One could be forgiven for thinking that such people are are narcissistic pessimists, flicking through each page alone at night, delighting in the Earth&amp;rsquo;s sorry state and egging-on its gradual demise. Humans are by nature optimistic beasts, so taking the world&amp;rsquo;s broad burdens onto our slender shoulders can seem to go against the grain. This is arguably especially so now that there is so much information about future threats: past apocalyptics had it comparatively easy, relying on magical interpretations of ancient texts and gut feeling. Now confronted with a vast and complex body of peer-reviewed literature from many fields suggesting that things are not going so well at the system level, the continued popularity of more leisurely exploits, such as golf or consumerism is understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, others enjoy the challenge of confronting reality head-on, whatever it might throw up. Satisfaction and even life guidance can emerge from a broad perspective. Falling firmly into the latter category, I reacted with relish, not trepidation, when this hardback arrived on my desk. Having sought-out, read and even reviewed (see Lovelace 2011) equally charming titles such as The Long Descent (Greer 2008), Blackout (Heinberg 2009) and Escaping Vesuvius (Douthwaite 2011), I imagined Friedrich&amp;rsquo;s first book would be light hearted by comparison. It quickly dawned it would not. The author is unwilling to mince words or sugar-coat the message at any stage: “why is there so little being done about climate change and energy scarcity”, when each “has the potential of jeopardizing not only industrial society as we know it but … our core civilisational values” (p. viii)? Friedrichs proclaims that “Facing the future is not for wimps” (p. xi) and proceeds to tackle the world&amp;rsquo;s problems with a clipped, direct style. The tone is upbeat despite the subject matter.
After the bravado of this opening, the first chapter, in which the historical background of Limits to Growth and Malthusianism are described, could seem a little underwhelming to the experienced apocalyptic. Things quickly pick up in chapter two which presents, in impressive brevity, the scale of the energy security and climate change threats. Friedrich&amp;rsquo;s writing contains meticulous attention to detail, made more impressive by the scale and breadth of the topics he tackles. The topic of carbon lock-in exemplifies this detail: “If present trends continue, carbon lock-in is on track to rise to 100 percent by 2017” (p. 26), meaning that built infrastructure completed by 2017 alone will have the potential to exceed the &amp;lsquo;safe&amp;rsquo; 450 ppm CO2 targets, even if no additional roads, mines or power stations are built beyond that point. In comparison with authors who prefer to use abstract terms and metaphor to describe the same issues (e.g. Eisenstein 2012; Kunstler 2006), Friedrich&amp;rsquo;s insistence on evidence and precision is, again, refreshing.
The brilliance of the book lies in its ability to glean insight about the future from past precedent. Friedrich&amp;rsquo;s does not take this approach lightly and is fully aware of the method&amp;rsquo;s limitations: “careful inference from historical cases is the worst research strategy except for all others” (p. 83). Specifically, the author rebuts more narrowly &amp;lsquo;scientific&amp;rsquo; approaches as as pathway to envision the future: “An insistent critic might further object that formal modeling is a better strategy to study the social and political effects of disruptive energy scarcity. I respectfully disagree … it is an illusion to assume that modeling leads to more directly applicable and unequivocal results” (p. 82).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Friedrichs means by this is not that science is a weak foundation on which to construct visions of the future; simply that it has little to say on the political and economic changes resulting from more quantifiable features such as average temperatures and oil well depletion rates, that will likely have the largest impacts on peoples&amp;rsquo; lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapters 3 and 4, which use past instances of climate change and energy scarcity as analogues for the future, respectively, are thus the core of the book. The former harnesses the archaeological record in Iceland and Greenland to illustrate how changes in temperature can wreak havoc on food supplies with knock-on consequences for socio-economic systems and culture. Friedrichs rejects environmental determinism, however: it was the society-level coping strategies of Icelandic culture that allowed it to survive the Little Ice Age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most impressive use of the historical analogy is presented in the subsequent chapter. This builds on an academic paper (Friedrichs, 2011) to discuss the implications of previous societal reactions to fuel shocks to our own situation. Interwar Japan and post-Soviet North Korea and Cuba are used to exemplify three contrasting responses to rapid declines in oil availability: militarism, autarky and adaptation, respectfully. Again, Friedrich&amp;rsquo;s meticulous yet concise use of evidence is his saving grace here. Rather than wallow in whether or not we are &amp;lsquo;doomed&amp;rsquo;, a brisk description of what actually happened in these dramatic situations is harnessed to provide dense nuggets of insight about how different parts of the world might adapt to energy shortages or rationing. Although Cuba&amp;rsquo;s is clearly the most preferable, there is no attempt to gloss-over the hardships of community-driven coping strategies or the cynical merits of more totalitarian responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are informative analogies indeed. So why are we not acting on them? Why do we not take pre-emptive action to mitigate the inevitable future declines in energy consumption now rather than being forced to in the future? The answers are provided in chapter 6 which is, in my opinion the book&amp;rsquo;s finest and most important contribution. “The moral economy of inaction” is a sweeping synthesis of social and psychological explanations for lack of action to mitigation civilisation level crisis, despite mounting evidence of trouble ahead. Based on a paper published in Philosophical Psychology (Friedrichs, 2012), the chapter explains with clarity and force how human nature tends to focus on the &amp;lsquo;here and now&amp;rsquo;, pushing systemic problems into the future. Friedrichs masterfully employs metaphor to explain complex psychological processes in lay terms, concluding that denial has set-in and is extremely difficult to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chapter is disquieting because it contains the admission that climate and energy crises are seen by the author as intractable and that “we have already passed the point of no return” (p. 160). The interesting thing about this admission is that it can act, as Friedrich&amp;rsquo;s himself acknowledges, as a self-fulfilling prophecy - if the issues are seen as intractable, denial becomes a logical solution to minimise pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being a self-confessed pessimist, Friedrichs wrote the final chapter for optimists. “Where to go from here” rejects wishful Utopian thinking and sketches out what a solution would look like in the abstract terms: it must be global, involving “radical transformations of our political, legal and economic subsystems” (p. 172). There is a potential for terrible atrocities to occur as a result of future ‘eco-scarcity’ yet these depressing outcomes are far from inevitable. Hope can even be found in the case of collapse, as underlined by reference to Greer’s magnificent vision, The Ecotechnic Future (Greer 2009) in the book’s closing section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, The Future is not what it used to be provides a potent antidote to wishful thinking about the scale of global problems and a brutally honest high-level assessment of humanity&amp;rsquo;s failure to act. For pessimists there is much to confirm one&amp;rsquo;s world-view and insight into how to avoid the traps of despair or denial. For optimists the book is a gruelling but ultimately enlightening experience. Falling into the latter camp, I found the book a dark masterpiece. A sober check against reckless hope, it contains a message that anyone interested in civilisation&amp;rsquo;s long-term future needs to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Douthwaite, R. J., Heinberg, R., &amp;amp; Fallon, G. 2011. Fleeing Vesuvius: Overcoming the    Risks of Economic and Environmental Collapse. New Society Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eisenstein, C. 2011. Sacred Economics: Money, Gift, and Society in the Age of   Transition. Evolver Editions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedrichs, J. 2010. ‘Global energy crunch: How different parts of the world would react to a peak oil scenario’. Energy Policy, 38(8): 4562–4569.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedrichs, J. 2012. ‘Useful lies: The twisted rationality of denial’. Philosophical    Psychology, ahead of print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greer, J. M. 2008. The Long Descent. New Society Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greer, J. M. 2009. The Ecotechnic Future: Envisioning a Post-Peak World. Aztext Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heinberg, R. 2009. Blackout: coal, climate and the last energy crisis. New Society Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kunstler, J. H. 2006. The Long Emergency: Surviving the End of Oil, Climate Change, and Other Converging Catastrophes of the Twenty-First Century. Grove/Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2011. ‘The Ecotechnic Future’. Now Then, 37: April     &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/issue-37/the-ecotechnic-future/&#34;&gt;http://nowthenmagazine.com/issue-37/the-ecotechnic-future/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving house by bicycle trailer</title>
      <link>/2013/10/13/moving-house-by-bicycle-trailer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/13/moving-house-by-bicycle-trailer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2009 I moved from York to Sheffield to start a PhD on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://e-futures.group.shef.ac.uk/page/home/&#34;&gt;Energy Futures&lt;/a&gt; 4 year Doctoral Training Centre.
Young and naive, some friends and I decided to do it by bicycle, with one bicycle trailer filled to the brim and 4 large panniers carrying most of my stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 years later and I&amp;rsquo;ve moved again, this time to Leeds. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a new a job at Leeds University,
 working on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geotalisman.org/&#34;&gt;Geotalisman&lt;/a&gt; project in the department of geography.
Older and hopefully wiser, I decided to move house by bicycle again: it&amp;rsquo;s shorter than the trip to York
(40 miles, not 60), I was more organised with planning (providing a month&amp;rsquo;s notice for friends and
family to attend and after 4 years in Sheffield I knew many people who would be up for the ride.
To make it more exciting, this time we brought music, in the form of a 12v sound system.
See the map, words, images and video below for the full low-down on this epic ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.gpsies.com/mapOnly.do?fileId=nueyoqzfqmingzgc&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-preparation-and-kit&#34;&gt;Introduction: preparation and kit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first stage was to recruit people. With a month&amp;rsquo;s notice, I managed to get around 15 people to
sign-up to the challenge. One issue for some people was lack of a suitable bicycle, so additional
ones were found and leant out. The best of these was a large tandem leant to me by a friend.
Trailers would be a major limiting factor for most people, but, as a member of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ewb.shef.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;EWB Sheffield&lt;/a&gt; who had helped on the bike trailer project, this was
less of an issue. We borrowed one trailer from EWB, and the other one was my own, purchased
from Ebay &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebay.co.uk/bhp/bicycle-trailer&#34;&gt;for around £60&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to set-off at 11 am. But it took almost an hour for to say final goodbyes, for everyone to
sort their stuff out and to decide who would be riding which
bikes. So it was essentially a midday start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stage-one-navigating-the-urban-jungle&#34;&gt;Stage one: navigating the urban jungle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting out of any major city is usually a challenge by bicycle, and Sheffield is no
exception, with the giant M1 dominating the norther route.
Fortunately we were ably guided for the first 10 miles or so by Sustrans Ranger
Simon Geller, who took us safely out via Northern General hospital and out onto
the car-free &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sustrans.org.uk/ncn/map/route/trans-pennine-trail-central&#34;&gt;Trans Pennine Trail&lt;/a&gt; to Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a major relief to get off the road, despite the hassle of hauling the big
bike trailers over the barriers - see video below.
After that the route was quite tranquil until, realising we were behind schedule,
we decided to just get onto the A61 for the final 5 miles to Barnesley,
where we had agreed to meet other people and from where people could go home early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stage-two-barnesley-to-wakefield&#34;&gt;Stage two: Barnesley to Wakefield&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were all quite tired in Barnesley, so a good rest was had by all in the
lush sunshine. Our only puncture of the trip was fixed, we ate and waited for
Nokolai - a new recuit from Leeds, who would help out greatly with lugging the trailers.
By the time we set off again it was almost 5. Conscious of the need to go faster to
arrive before sunset, we changed our route plan completely and decided just to
get our heads down and pedal along the A61 all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference in speed was noticeable. With fresh legs towing the bicycle trailers
and some of the less experienced cyclists leaving us in Barnesley it felt like we
were flying. The road is wide and flat, so it did not feel especially dangerous.
Cycling in convoy is probably safer anyway because people notice a flock of cyclists
more than a single one or two. There was a hard climb up to Wakefield where we
had a number of small stops. The overall feeling was &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s just get there&amp;rdquo; so
we pressed on, after another couple of people headed to the train station.
The proximity of rail stations to the route was one of its major advantages,
allowing people to leave when they wanted to, and meaning that setting off
was not such a major commitment. It was all downhill from Wakefield, or
so we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-final-straight-into-leeds&#34;&gt;The final straight: into Leeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dusk descended, the group re-united. With various distractions, we had become
dispersed on the fast downhill stretch directly north of Wakefield. As the traffic
volume increased again near central Leeds, and as our level of visibility decreased
it made sense to stick together. At this stage we turned the volume up on the
bicycle trailer soundsystem. This helped a great deal to raise spirits that were flagging
after a longer than expected ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived in Leeds city centre at around 8pm. Knackered, we went directly to
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wharfchambers.org/&#34;&gt;Wharf Chambers&lt;/a&gt; for a pint and some food.
Before I knew it we were watching live music, most of my Sheffield friends had
gone back after heartfelt goodbyes, and it was approaching midnight.
But we still had two bicycle trailers to get back to my final destination, which was still another
mile away, uphill. This final stretch was a real slog, but, thanks to Nikolai&amp;rsquo;s
indominatable spirit we made it there before 12. Finally I was home!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-move-house-by-bike-trailer&#34;&gt;Why move house by bike trailer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the extra hassle involved, you may wonder why I went to all these lengths.
A van could have done the job in under 2 hours, with a lot less sweat and in fact
I used this option a week later to move residual stuff that I could not
fit into the trailers. So why bother?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason for doing this was social: instead of having a big &amp;lsquo;piss-up&amp;rsquo; to see
me off I much preferred people stayed in the night before. That way I got to have
a sober conversation with some of my best friends in Sheffield whilst doing something fun.
For a few people on the ride, it was the furthest they had ever travelled by bicycle, and
this alone was worth-it for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason was that bicycle trailer moves are cheap. To hire a van can easily cost £100 for the day,
and the price of breakfast for the ride (and buying many people drinks in Leeds) was considerably less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, bicycling in general is healthy. It&amp;rsquo;s good for you because you get your heart pumping and
some fresh air. It&amp;rsquo;s healthy for the environment too, as you get to leave the car at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving house by bicycle trailer was one of the the most enjoyable experiences
of 2013 for me. Being surrounded by friends, music and sunshine was infinitely
preferable to the van-based alternative. The even also brought people together in
a way that simply going out and drinking alcohol cannot. It was fun, free (in every
sense of the word) but definitely not fast, so if you have a tight schedule to move
bicycle trailers may not be the best way forward. There are also obvious physical limits
in how far you can actually move bulky items in a single day and 40 miles was already
pushing the limit for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would strongly recommend anyone who&amp;rsquo;s moving house to a not too distant
new location to consider bicycle trailers. They are so much more fun and
sociable than just jumping in a van, you just can&amp;rsquo;t go wrong.
If this little article on the matter has not persuaded you, check the video
below, sounds and all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be forever grateful to all the people who helped out with this move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6a8QLiC4LV8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at FOSS4G 2013</title>
      <link>/2013/09/22/presentation-at-foss4g-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/22/presentation-at-foss4g-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I presented last Thursday at &lt;a href=&#34;http://2013.foss4g.org/&#34;&gt;FOSS4G&lt;/a&gt;, THE conference to go to for Free Open Source Software for Geo applications (get it?). It was an interesting event, with hundreds of delegates dressing up in one form or another as Robin Hood, fantastic food and a very wide range of talks. Just take a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://2013.foss4g.org/conf/programme/daily/2/&#34;&gt;second day&lt;/a&gt; of talks: packed to the rafters with sessions, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://2013.foss4g.org/conf/programme/sessions/36/&#34;&gt;mine&lt;/a&gt;, on visualisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A link to the slides is provided below. With these as a backdrop, I discussed the various techniques I had used to &amp;lsquo;get my work out there&amp;rsquo;, to make it as accessible as possible to other people, especially those not involved in the stuffy world of academia. There was good feedback from the audience. Ben Hennig suggesting that I coloured only populated areas on my visualisations, to avoid attributing excessive visual importance to large uninhabited spaces. This technique can be witnessed to great effect on &lt;a href=&#34;http://oliverobrien.co.uk/2012/02/&#34;&gt;Oliver O&amp;rsquo;brien&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An illustration of visualisation to understand the spatial distribution of transport energy use, taken from my &lt;a href=&#34;http://etheses.whiterose.ac.uk/5027/&#34;&gt;thesis&lt;/a&gt;, is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Robinlovelace/thesis-reproducible/master/Figures/prop-trans-energy.png&#34; alt=&#34;prop-trans-energy.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the talks were recorded, so if you are REALLY interested in the talk, you should also be able to listen to it - keep an eye out on the FOSS4G website to see when these go up live. For now, sit back and enjoy the visuals (see the slides at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/robinlovelace1985/visualising-the-energy-costs-of-commuting-26396493&#34;&gt;slideshare.net&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/26396493&#34; width=&#34;427&#34; height=&#34;356&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; style=&#34;border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom:5px&#34;&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/robinlovelace1985/visualising-the-energy-costs-of-commuting-26396493&#34; title=&#34;Visualising the energy costs of commuting&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Visualising the energy costs of commuting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/robinlovelace1985&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Robin Lovelace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
--&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;welcome&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Welcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my website. The aim is to provide a place for getting my work and ideas out there quickly and better linked-in with the wider world. I hope you find something here of use and interest. Enjoy your visit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;about-me&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a geographer and environmental scientist specialising in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crcpress.com/Spatial-Microsimulation-with-R/Lovelace-Dumont/p/book/9781498711548&#34;&gt;spatial data analysis&lt;/a&gt; and computing, especially &lt;a href=&#34;https://csgillespie.github.io/efficientR/&#34;&gt;R programming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based at the Leeds Institute for Transport Studies (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.its.leeds.ac.uk/people/r.lovelace&#34;&gt;ITS&lt;/a&gt;) I have a strong interest in transport modelling. This is described in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/102373/1/urban-travel-rl.pdf&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.e-elgar.com/shop/forecasting-urban-travel&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on the subject by &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Boyce and Williams (2015)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I studied Geography at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bristol.ac.uk/geography/&#34;&gt;University of Bristol&lt;/a&gt; after moving out of my home town of Hereford where I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://weobleyhigh.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Weobley High School&lt;/a&gt;, out in rural Northwest Herefordshire, and then Hereford &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hereford.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Sixth Form College&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an early age I enjoyed travelling. Since moving to Bristol to settling in Leeds for my current job I have moved 3 times:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To Salamanca in 2006 for a year studying at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usal.es/&#34;&gt;Universidad de Salamanca&lt;/a&gt; on the Erasmus scheme, where I learned Spanish, before completing my degree in Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To York in 2008 for a scholarship on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.york.ac.uk/study/postgraduate/courses/msc-environmental-science-management/&#34;&gt;Environmental Science and Management&lt;/a&gt; master’s course at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.york.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;University of York&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To Sheffield in 2009 to do a PhD in energy and transport at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://shef.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;University of Sheffield&lt;/a&gt; as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://e-futures.group.shef.ac.uk/page/home/&#34;&gt;E-Futures&lt;/a&gt; centre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6a8QLiC4LV8&#34;&gt;by bicycle trailer!&lt;/a&gt;) from Sheffield to Leeds in summer 2013 for a post-doctorate job in Geospatial Data Analysis and Simulation (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.researchcatalogue.esrc.ac.uk/grants/RES-576-25-0039/read&#34;&gt;TALISMAN&lt;/a&gt;). A year later I got a job at the Leeds Institute for Data Analytics (&lt;a href=&#34;http://lida.leeds.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;LIDA&lt;/a&gt;) where I am still based alongside my role in ITS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been based at the Leeds Institute for Transport Studies (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.its.leeds.ac.uk&#34;&gt;ITS&lt;/a&gt;) since September 2016 as a University Academic Fellow in Transport and Big Data. Here I work on researching the energy impacts of transport systems, modelling the uptake of sustainable transport uptake, new methods on transport geography and visualizing transport futures at a local level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;applied-work&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Applied work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve applied my skills to a number of projects with real-world applications, most recently the Propensity to Cycle Tool (PCT) for the Department for Transport &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Lovelace et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt;. The PCT is a national project which maps future cycling potential with the aim of helping to design more sustainable cities. A central output of the PCT is a publicly accessible map. If you live in England, you can check out current and potential future levels of cycling in your local area by visiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pct.bike/&#34;&gt;www.pct.bike&lt;/a&gt; and clicking on where you live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also develop &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr&#34;&gt;stplanr&lt;/a&gt;, an R package for sustainable transport planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;about-this-website&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About this website&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website was built using open source software. It uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, a static website generator written in Go, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;, an R package by Yihui Xie writing posts that contain embedded code. Its source code can be found at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rbind/robinlovelace&#34;&gt;github.com/rbind/robinlovelace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in my earlier work, please check-out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other posts by me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-bloggers.com/author/robin-lovelace-r/&#34;&gt;R-Bloggers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My old Wordpress site at &lt;a href=&#34;https://robinlovelace.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;robinlovelace.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Older posts hosted on an &lt;a href=&#34;http://robinlovelace.net/old-site.html&#34;&gt;earlier version of this website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My YouTube channel at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/robinlovelace&#34;&gt;youtube.com/robinlovelace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-boyce_forecasting_2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boyce, David E., and Huw C. W. L. Williams. 2015. &lt;em&gt;Forecasting Urban Travel: Past, Present and Future&lt;/em&gt;. Edward Elgar Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-lovelace_propensity_2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, Robin, Anna Goodman, Rachel Aldred, Nikolai Berkoff, Ali Abbas, and James Woodcock. 2017. “The Propensity to Cycle Tool: An Open Source Online System for Sustainable Transport Planning.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Transport and Land Use&lt;/em&gt; 10 (1). doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&#34;&gt;10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publications/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;!-- This is a list of my publications to date: --&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;books&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Nowosad, J., Meunchow, J., 2019. Geocomputation with R. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crcpress.com/Geocomputation-with-R/Lovelace-Nowosad-Munchow/p/book/9781138304512&#34;&gt;CRC Press&lt;/a&gt;. Available in physical form on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Geocomputation-Chapman-Hall-Robin-Lovelace/dp/1138304514/&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://wordery.com/geocomputation-with-r-robin-lovelace-9781138304512&#34;&gt;Wordery&lt;/a&gt; and online at &lt;a href=&#34;http://geocompr.robinlovelace.net/&#34;&gt;robinlovelace.net&lt;/a&gt;. Solutions website: &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocompr.github.io/&#34;&gt;geocompr.github.io&lt;/a&gt; Source code: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/robinlovelace/geocompr&#34;&gt;github.com/robinlovelace/geocompr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gillespie, C., Lovelace, R., 2016. Efficient R Programming: A Practical Guide to Smarter Programming. &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920047995.do&#34;&gt;O’Reilly Media&lt;/a&gt;, and as a free learning resource from its &lt;a href=&#34;https://csgillespie.github.io/efficientR/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Dumont, M., 2016. Spatial microsimulation with R. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crcpress.com/Spatial-Microsimulation-with-R/Lovelace-Dumont/p/book/9781498711548&#34;&gt;CRC Press&lt;/a&gt; and (to see source code) &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/spatial-microsim-book&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., &amp;amp; McLoughlin, A., 2014. Engineering in Development: Transport. Engineers Without Borders (UK), &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/77557/&#34;&gt;Draft&lt;/a&gt; (high resolution images - 24 Mb). &lt;a href=&#34;http://robinlovelace.net/publications/eind-transport-mcloughlin-lovelace-2014-final.pdf&#34;&gt;Final version (2.4 Mb - recommended)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;journal-articles&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Journal articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodman, A., Fridman-Rojas, I., Aldred, R., Woodcock, J., Lovelace, R., 2019. Scenarios of cycling to school in England, and associated health and carbon impacts: Application of the ‘Propensity to Cycle Tool’. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2214140518301257&#34;&gt;Journal of Transport &amp;amp; Health&lt;/a&gt; 12, Pages 263-278. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jth.2019.01.008&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jth.2019.01.008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Morgan, M., Hama, L., Padgham, Mark, Padgham, M, 2019. stats19 A package for working with open road crash data. Journal of Open Source Software 4, 1181. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01181&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01181&lt;/a&gt;. Package website: &lt;a href=&#34;https://itsleeds.github.io/stats19/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://itsleeds.github.io/stats19/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilson, T., Lovelace, R., Evans, A.J., 2019. A Path Toward the Use of Trail Users’ Tweets to Assess Effectiveness of the Environmental Stewardship Scheme: An Exploratory Analysis of the Pennine Way National Trail. Appl. Spatial Analysis 1–29. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12061-016-9201-7&#34;&gt;doi:10.1007/s12061-016-9201-7&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roxburgh, Nicholas, et al. “Characterising Climate Change Discourse on Social Media during Extreme Weather Events.” &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0959378018305776&#34;&gt;Global Environmental Change&lt;/a&gt;, vol. 54, Jan. 2019, pp. 50–60. ScienceDirect, &lt;a href=&#34;doi:10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2018.11.004&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2018.11.004&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Ellison, R., 2018. stplanr: A Package for Transport Planning. The R Journal 10, 7–23. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.32614/RJ-2018-053&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.32614/RJ-2018-053&lt;/a&gt;. Package home: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ropensci/stplanr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsivais, P., Francis, O., Lovelace, R., Chang, M., Strachan, E., Burgoine, T.H. 2018. Data visualisation to support obesity policy: case studies of data tools for planning and transport policy in the UK. Apollo - University of Cambridge Repository. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.17863/cam.34009&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.17863/cam.34009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morton, C., Lovelace, R., Philips, I., Anable, J., 2018. Fuel price differentials and car ownership: A spatial analysis of diesel cars in Northern Ireland. Transportation Research Part D: Transport and Environment 63, 755–768. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trd.2018.07.008&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trd.2018.07.008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woodcock, J., Abbas, A., Ullrich, A., Tainio, M., Lovelace, R., Sá, T.H., Westgate, K., Goodman, A., 2018. Development of the Impacts of Cycling Tool (ICT): A modelling study and web tool for evaluating health and environmental impacts of cycling uptake. PLOS Medicine 15, e1002622. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1002622&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1002622&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morton, C., Lovelace, R., Anable, J., 2017. Exploring the effect of local transport policies on the adoption of low emission vehicles: Evidence from the London Congestion Charge and Hybrid Electric Vehicles. Transport Policy 60, 34–46. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tranpol.2017.08.007&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tranpol.2017.08.007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aldred, R., Watson, T., Lovelace, R., Woodcock, J., 2017. Barriers to investing in cycling: Stakeholder views from England. Transportation Research Part A: Policy and Practice. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2017.11.003&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2017.11.003&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreno-Monroy, A.I., Lovelace, R., Ramos, F.R., 2017. Public transport and school location impacts on educational inequalities: Insights from São Paulo. Journal of Transport Geography 67. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2017.08.012&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2017.08.012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Padgham, M., Lovelace, R., Salmon, M., Rudis, B., 2017. osmdata. The Journal of Open Source Software 2. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00305&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00305&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, A., Lovelace, R., Birkin, M., 2017. Population Synthesis with Quasirandom Integer Sampling. Journal of Artificial Societies and Social Simulation 20, 14. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.18564/jasss.3550&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.18564/jasss.3550&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Goodman, A., Aldred, R., Berkoff, N., Abbas, A., Woodcock, J., 2017. The Propensity to Cycle Tool: An open source online system for sustainable transport planning. Journal of Transport and Land Use 10. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&#34;&gt;doi:10.5198/jtlu.2016.862&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source code: &lt;a href=&#34;github.com/npct/pct-shiny&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;github.com/npct/pct-shiny&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Roberts, H., Kellar, I., 2016. Who, where, when: the demographic and geographic distribution of bicycle crashes in West Yorkshire. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S136984781500039X&#34;&gt;Transportation Research Part F: Traffic Psychology and Behaviour, Bicycling and bicycle safety 41, Part B&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trf.2015.02.010&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.trf.2015.02.010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open access version: &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/83930/&#34;&gt;eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/83930/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Source code: &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/Robinlovelace/bikeR&#34;&gt;github.com/Robinlovelace/bikeR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uttley, J., Lovelace, R., 2016. Cycling promotion schemes and long-term behavioural change: A case study from the University of Sheffield. Case Studies on Transport Policy 4. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cstp.2016.01.001&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.cstp.2016.01.001&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open access version: &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/79074/7/cycle-challenge-lovelace10.pdf&#34;&gt;eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/79074&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., 2016. Mapping out the future of cycling. Get Britain Cycling 5, 22–24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Access version: &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/100080/1/Get_Britain_Cycling_2016_PCT.pdf&#34;&gt;eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/100080&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Birkin, M., Cross, P., Clarke, M., 2016. From Big Noise to Big Data: Toward the Verification of Large Data sets for Understanding Regional Retail Flows. Geographical Analysis 48, &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/gean.12081/full&#34;&gt;59–81. doi:10.1111/gean.12081&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Ballas, D., Birkin, M.M.H., van Leeuwen, E., Ballas, D., van Leeuwen, E., Birkin, M.M.H., 2015. Evaluating the performance of Iterative Proportional Fitting for spatial microsimulation: new tests for an established technique. &lt;a href=&#34;http://jasss.soc.surrey.ac.uk/18/2/21.html&#34;&gt;Journal of Artificial Societies and Social Simulation 18, 21&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Malleson, N., Harland, K., &amp;amp; Birkin, M., 2014. Geotagged tweets to inform a spatial interaction model: a case study of museums. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1403.5118&#34;&gt;arXiv preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Ballas, D., &amp;amp; Watson, M. 2014. A spatial microsimulation approach for the analysis of commuter patterns: from individual to regional levels. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Transport Geography, 34, 282-296.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2013.07.008&#34;&gt;doi: 10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2013.07.008&lt;/a&gt;. Preprint &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/smsim-4-transport.pdf&#34;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., &amp;amp; Philips, I. 2014. The ‘oil vulnerability’of commuter patterns: A case study from Yorkshire and the Humber, UK. &lt;em&gt;Geoforum&lt;/em&gt;, 51, 169-182 &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.geoforum.2013.11.005&#34;&gt;doi: 10.1016/j.geoforum.2013.11.005&lt;/a&gt; . Preprint &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/77115/&#34;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., &amp;amp; Ballas, D. 2013. “Truncate, replicate, sample”: A method for creating integer weights for spatial microsimulation. Computers, Environment and Urban Systems, 41, 1–11. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2013.03.004&#34;&gt;doi10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2013.03.004&lt;/a&gt;. Preprint available via &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1303.5228&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/truncate-replicate-sample-preprint.pdf&#34;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., &amp;amp; Temple, L. 2012. Carbon Capture and Storage: bury the myth and focus on alternatives. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ippr.org/publication/55/9674/metis-volume-3&#34;&gt;Metis&lt;/a&gt;, 3. Full article available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/CCS-myth-IPPR.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R., Beck, S. B. M., Watson, M., &amp;amp; Wild, A. 2011. Assessing the energy implications of replacing car trips with bicycle trips in Sheffield, UK. &lt;em&gt;Energy Policy, 39(4)&lt;/em&gt;, 2075-2087. Elsevier. &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.enpol.2011.01.051&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.enpol.2011.01.051&lt;/a&gt; preprint &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/modal-shift-preprint.pdf&#34;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2008. Energy: efficiency gains alone won’t reduce emissions. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;455&lt;/em&gt;(7212), 460. Nature Publishing Group. &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.1038/455461a&#34;&gt;doi:10.1038/455461a&lt;/a&gt;, also available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/Lovelace%20-%202008%20-%20Energy%20efficiency%20gains%20alone%20won%27t%20reduce%20emissions.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;book-chapters&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Book chapters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheshire, J. &amp;amp; Lovelace, R., 2014. Spatial data visualisation with R. In &lt;em&gt;Geocomputation, a Practical Primer&lt;/em&gt;. Preprint available online via &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/geocomPP/sdv/raw/master/chapter.pdf&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/274697165_Spatial_data_visualisation_with_R&#34;&gt;ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;printed-magazine-articles&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Printed magazine articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2014. Jornadas de SIG Libre: A European Digital Mapping Conference. Geoinformatics, 17(4), 12. Available online from &lt;a href=&#34;http://fluidbook.geoinformatics.com/GEO-Informatics_4_2014/#/12/&#34;&gt;Geoinformatics.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--TODO: add link2 preprint--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doctoral Students Who Publish. University of Sheffield Doctoral Times, Spring 2013. p. 6. Sheffield. Magazine &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/polopoly_fs/1.271737!/file/DoctoralTimes-Spring2013.pdf&#34;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Yer Bike. &lt;em&gt;Now Then&lt;/em&gt;, December 2012. Sheffield. Available &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/issue-57/on-yer-bike/&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mystery of Sheffield’s steepest hill. &lt;em&gt;Now Then&lt;/em&gt;, February 2012. Sheffield. Available online from &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/sheffield/issue-47/hills/&#34;&gt;nowthenmagazine.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bike trailers. &lt;em&gt;Now Then&lt;/em&gt;, September 2011. Sheffield. Available online as &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/issue-42/bike-trailers/&#34;&gt;html&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/Trailer12-accepted.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ecotechnic Future. &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/sheffield/issue-37/the-ecotechnic-future/&#34;&gt;Now Then Magazine&lt;/a&gt;, March 2011. Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear. &lt;em&gt;Now Then&lt;/em&gt;, November 2010, p. 22-23. Sheffield. &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/issue-33/fear/&#34;&gt;Html&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/Ecotechnic-NT-37.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/77321/13/lovelacecycle-touring.pdf&#34;&gt;Pdf version&lt;/a&gt; also available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy futures. &lt;em&gt;Now Then&lt;/em&gt;, June 2010, p. 16-17. Sheffield. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/Energy_futures.pdf&#34;&gt;Html&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/wp-content/themes/nowthen/backissues/nt27_jun10.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;book-reviews&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Book reviews&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transport Justice Designing Fair Transport Systems by Karel Martens. 2017. New York Routledge £40.99. ISBN 978-0415638326 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0966692319304193&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Transport Geography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2019.05.011&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2019.05.011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sage Handbook of Transport Studies, Jean-Paul Rodrigue, Theo Notteboom, Jon Shaw (Eds.). Sage, London 2013. £95, Hardback, ISBN: 978-1-84920-789-8, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Transport Geography&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2014.05.002&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2014.05.002&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future Is not what it used to be: a review for optimists. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Values&lt;/em&gt;. 23, 2, 114. Preprint &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/77320/&#34;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sacred-economics.com/&#34;&gt;Sacred Economics&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Now Then Magazine&lt;/em&gt;, 59, February, p. 8. &lt;a href=&#34;http://nowthenmagazine.com/issue-59/sacred-economics/&#34;&gt;Available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;online-magazines&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Online magazines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. and Temple, L. 2012. Carbon capture and storage: time to bury the myth? &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rtcc.org/2012/10/02/carbon-capture-and-storage-time-to-bury-the-myth/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Responding to Climate Change&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 15 October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2011. Assessing the energy implication of political intervention. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theoildrum.com/node/7798#more&#34;&gt;The Oil Drum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2010, Cycle-touring: a vision of post-peak holidays? &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://campfire.theoildrum.com/node/6396&#34;&gt;The Oil Drum&lt;/a&gt;: Campfire&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2010. How to Set Up and Run a Bicycle Repair Company. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://campfire.theoildrum.com/node/5976&#34;&gt;The Oil Drum&lt;/a&gt;: Campfire&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;user-guides-and-tutorials&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;User guides and tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2014. Introducing spatial microsimulation with R: a practical. In-depth tutorial on spatial microsimulation for an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncrm.ac.uk/training/show.php?article=4786&#34;&gt;NCRM Short Course&lt;/a&gt; and available as an &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.ncrm.ac.uk/3348/&#34;&gt;NCRM working paper&lt;/a&gt;. Latest version &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/smsim-course/raw/master/handout.pdf&#34;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2014. Harnessing Open Street Map Data with R and QGIS. Leeds School of Geography practical Working Paper. Available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://elogeo.nottingham.ac.uk/xmlui/browse?value=Lovelace%2C+Robin&amp;amp;type=author&#34;&gt;EloGeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. and Cheshire, J. 2014 and ongoing). Introduction to visualising spatial data in R. Tutorial for NCRM Short Course. Updated version hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace/Creating-maps-in-R&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, original hosted by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.ncrm.ac.uk/3295/&#34;&gt;National Centre for Research Methods&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2013. Supplementary information: a user manual for the integerisation of IPF weights using R, 1–18. Available online on arXiv or from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personal.leeds.ac.uk/~georl/papers/supplement-3.pdf&#34;&gt;University of Leeds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2013. Open Source Data and Methods: A tutorial using crowd-sourced data for store location analysis (p. 20). Sheffield. Download from &lt;a href=&#34;http://robinlovelace.net/publications/osm-tutorial-final-2.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;thesis&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovelace, R. 2014. The energy costs of commuting: a spatial microsimulation approach. University of Sheffield. Viva (16/12/2013) examined by professors &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ucl.ac.uk/bartlett/people/?school=casa&amp;amp;upi=JMBAT23&#34;&gt;Michael Batty&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/geography/staff/pattie_charles&#34;&gt;Charles Pattie&lt;/a&gt;. Entire thesis document and example code and data available from a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/robinlovelace/thesis-reproducible&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;further-info&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on my publications please see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.co.uk/citations?user=xDJHVCAAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5679-6536&#34;&gt;Orcid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Robinlovelace&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, where I publish most of the code I write for packages/papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selected presentations</title>
      <link>/slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/slides/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I’ve done dozens of presentations over the years.
This is a list of slides and further information from some of my favourites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/nurd.html#1&#34;&gt;Geocomputation with R Empower yourself with free software and geo* data&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keynote lecture for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/NWURday?src=hash&#34;&gt;Northwest Universities R Day&lt;/a&gt;, 2018-10-31&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/nurd.ogg&#34;&gt;Audio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;pedalea.html#1&#34;&gt;ICTs para la (ciclo)inclusión&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invited lecture in Chile at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://m.facebook.com/LabCambiarnos/?refid=17&#34;&gt;Seminario del Transporte a la Movilidad y Accesibilidad&lt;/a&gt; (in Spanish), 2018-10-05&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;cs-infra.html#1&#34;&gt;Severance, parallels and integration&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plenary lecture at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cyclingandsociety.org/2018programme/&#34;&gt;Cycling &amp;amp; Society conference&lt;/a&gt;, Bristol, 2018-09-06&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio from the talk is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robinlovelace.net/presentations/cs-infra.ogg&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;can-gds-save-world.html#1&#34;&gt;Can Geographic Data Save the World?&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invited seminar at the University of Liverpool’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/geographic-data-science/&#34;&gt;Geographic Data Science Lab&lt;/a&gt;, 2017-05-02&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/RobinLovelace/188175&#34;&gt;Cycling and transport policy: embedding active travel in every stage of the planning process&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keynote lecture at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hackney.gov.uk/cycling-conference&#34;&gt;Hackney Cycling Conference&lt;/a&gt;, 2016-06-10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>