<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Seminars, invited talks and workshops on Robin Lovelace&#39;s website. Energy. Transport. Technology. Change the World.</title>
    <link>/presentations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Seminars, invited talks and workshops on Robin Lovelace&#39;s website. Energy. Transport. Technology. Change the World.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/presentations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Geocomputation with R: from inception to physical book</title>
      <link>/presentations/geocompr-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/geocompr-launch/</guid>
      <description>Lecture and book launch, part of Leeds Digital Festival This talk will introduce Geocomputation with R, a new book on R for geographic data that has just been published. Aimed at people new to the subject, I’ll provide some examples to show the power of programming with open source software for high-performance, reproducible mapping and geographic analyis. I will cover a bit of the history but focus on visualisation, which is key to using data to understand the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keynote talk on geocomputation, SatRdays Newcastle</title>
      <link>/presentations/satrday-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/satrday-keynote/</guid>
      <description>Keynote talk at SatRdays Newcastle Geocomputation with R: Reproducible Geo* workflows, from getting data to making maps This talk will introduce Geocomputation with R, a new book on R for geographic data. It will demonstrate how far R has evolved as an environment for geographic data analysis and visualisation, and provide a taster of what is in the book and, more importantly, what is possible when &amp;lsquo;data science&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;GIS&amp;rsquo; meet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geocomputation with R: Empower yourself with geo data</title>
      <link>/presentations/nurd-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/nurd-keynote/</guid>
      <description> Keynote lecture for the Northwest Universities R Day, Manchester In this, titled Geocomputation with R: Empower yourself with free software and geo* data, I provide an overview of the evolving landscape for working with geographic data using open source, command-line driven software.
 Slides Audio   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited lecture: ICTs para la (ciclo)inclusión</title>
      <link>/presentations/icts-inclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/icts-inclusion/</guid>
      <description> Invited lecture in Chile at the Seminario del Transporte a la Movilidad y Accesibilidad (in Spanish)  Title: ICTs para la (ciclo)inclusión Slides (in Spanish)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Severance, parallels and integration</title>
      <link>/presentations/cycling-and-society-plenary/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/cycling-and-society-plenary/</guid>
      <description> Plenary lecture at the Cycling &amp;amp; Society conference, Bristol Talk on methods for estimating severance in active transport networks.
 Slides: Severance, parallels and integration Audio from the talk is available here   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited seminar: can geographic data save the world?</title>
      <link>/presentations/geocompr-jena/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/geocompr-jena/</guid>
      <description> This was the finale of a week of research collaboration and teaching at the Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena Institut für Geographie. During the study visit I also worked on Geocomputation with R with fellow co-author Jannes Muenchow and wrote a tutorial on route network analysis in R that can be found at https://github.com/Robinlovelace/geocomp-tranport-workshop
 Slides: Can Geographic Data Save the World?  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seminar: invited talk at Geographic Data Science lab</title>
      <link>/presentations/gds-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/gds-seminar/</guid>
      <description> Talk at the Geographic Data Science (GDS) Lab in Liverpool.
 Slides  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keynote: Cycling and transport policy</title>
      <link>/presentations/hackney-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentations/hackney-keynote/</guid>
      <description>Invited keynote lecture titled Cycling and transport policy: embedding active travel in every stage of the planning process, at the Hackney Cycling Conference - Slides</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>